<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the bankers and their creditors stated and examined by the rules of lawes, policy, and common reason, as it was inclosed in a letter to a friend / by a true lover of his King and country, and a sufferer for loyalty.</title>
            <author>Turner, Thomas, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11976561</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11976561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 519:52)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the bankers and their creditors stated and examined by the rules of lawes, policy, and common reason, as it was inclosed in a letter to a friend / by a true lover of his King and country, and a sufferer for loyalty.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Thomas, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing no. arbitrarily assigned, since it is difficult to distinguish between T3335 and T3336. Possibly the two are identical.</note>
                  <note>First letter signed: Sma. Ro. and postscript at end of work signed: S.R. both of which are a pseudonym for Thomas Turner. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Minnesota Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Banks and banking --  England --  History.</term>
               <term>Finance --  England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF THE BANKERS And their CREDITORS.</p>
            <p>Stated and Examined; By the Rules of Lawes, Policy, and common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it was incloſed in a Letter to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a true Lover of his King and Country, and a Sufferer for Loyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Ad Reges poteſtas omnium pertinet, ad ſingulos proprietas, <hi>Seneca de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificijs,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Cap. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Rex ad tutelam Legis, Corporum, &amp; Bonorum erectus eſt. <hi>Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour Forteſcue,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>cap. <hi>13.7.</hi> Rep. Calvin's Caſe, <hi>5.</hi> a</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Concilia callida &amp; audacia, prima froute laeta, tractatu dura, eventu triſtia.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eraſmus in Epiſtolis.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>That State is in ill condition, where the juſtly accuſed ſhall take Revenge of the juſt Accuſer, and where he that would ſave his Prince muſt ruine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Sir Walter Rawleigh's <hi>Prerogative of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Obedience to your Command, I have committed to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſome Notions I had conceived of the <hi>Bankers</hi> buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the calamitous dependants thereon. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you thought me (though concern'd enough) pretty warm in this Argument laſt time I diſcourſt it with you; and truly if hard uſages will make a wiſe man mad, the Effect it hath upon a Fool (as I am) may well want a name. I have <hi>I</hi> praiſe-God weather'd out all thoſe dreadful ſtorms which fell ſome years ſince upon the Loyal par y, (as you know) though with the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of my per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on and Eſtate, and this (if <hi>I</hi> may ſpeak it without Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) I did with conſtancy and joy, for though I could ſee then nothing but Tempeſts and Hurricanes without me,<note place="margin">Plin. in Pany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. ad Traja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num imperat. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>polit. Lib. 4. Cap 11.</hi> Raleighs Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog. of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in finc.</note> yet my mind was alwayes refreſht with ſereneties and calmneſs, triumphing that <hi>I</hi> was thought worthy at any rate, to ſuffer for ſo glorious a cauſe. After his Majeſties Happy Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, though neglected and deſpiſed, as many of far greater merit than my ſelf likewiſe were, we did all however poſſeſs our ſouls with patience (though wiſe men tell us that it was never accounted the best policy to diſmiſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſervers in point of Recompence with the ſatisfaction only of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the rewards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the next world). And now when we and our miſerable Families had thought to have protracted (at leaſt) a contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life with thoſe poor remainders, and broken pieces of our Fortunes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in one moment thoſe alſo are raviſht from ſome of us by our friends. By what name ſhall <hi>I</hi> expreſs this treatment? ſhall I call it a violation of the Widdowes Mite? or a breaking into the Alms-basket? no theſe reach it not, all nature cannot furniſh me with a ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>Sir miſtake me not, <hi>I</hi> would not be thought here to lay ſo great a calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the door of my dread Soveraign (a Prince in his own free nature, and unforc't inclination not to be paralleld for all Royal Graces) no Sir, the Law teaches me to conceive more Honourably of the King's Juſtice (by which his Throne is Eſtabliſht) and te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> me that whatſoever wrong is done to the Subject, is effected by miſinformations of his Majeſty,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.12.</note> and pernicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nihil aliud poteſt Rex in tearis</hi> (ſaith Bracton) <hi>cum ſit Dei miniſter &amp; vicarius niſi id ſolum quod de jure poteſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bracton lib. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> The King can do nothing ſeeing he is God<hi>'s</hi> Vicegerent, but that which he may lawfully do. <hi>Rex hoc ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non poteſt facere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cook <hi>d.</hi> 11. Rep. 72. a Magdalen col caſe.</note> 
               <hi>quod non poteſt injuſte agere</hi> (ſay the Judges in another Caſe) This one thing only the King cannot do, that he cannot do injuſtice (which yet is ſo far from impotency or imperfection, that it is a Character alſo of the Divinity). And therefore <hi>Markham</hi> Chief Juſtice of <hi>England</hi> told King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th. that he could not Arreſt any man for a miſdemeanour (as a Subject mought) becauſe if the King did wrong,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.4 b pet <hi>Huſſey</hi> ch. Juſtice d'An gliter.</note> the party could not have his Action againſt him; we receive Life and Vigour from the influences of Heaven, but Diſtempers proceed from the Vapours of the Earth, which vapours yet can convey no infection into thoſe Caleſtial bodies: Even ſo ſometimes the countenance of Princes may concur in the Execution of illegal advices, without ſharing in the Obliquity and injuſtice of them.</p>
            <p>The Poets have a witty Fable of <hi>Tireſias,</hi> the great Southſayer, that he foretold future events by the flying of birds, not that he did ſee the birds (for he was blind) but (ſay they) he had alwaies his Daughter <hi>Manto</hi> near at hand, who inform'd him of the manner of their flights, and according to her advertiſements, the Father evermore divined: The Mythology or Moral of this Fable is oftentimes applicable to the beſt and moſt virtuous Princes, they hear with other mens Ears, they ſee ſometimes thorough the ſpestacles of other mens eyes, and according to the colour of the glaſs, ſo is the object re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them; black or red, or perhaps white, whereas the true tincture of the thing may be clearly otherwiſe; and yet all this while the fault is not in the eye, but in the deceptive glaſs. If a falſe Light-houſe be erected near a dangerous Rock in the Sea, and in a dark and tempeſtuous night the Ship is ſteered that way, as to a ſafe Port, and thereupon ſuffereth wrack, no body can with any reaſon imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te this misfortune to the error or incogitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Pilot,</hi> or governour of the Veſſel, but rather to the malice and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of this wicked invention.<note place="margin">Seneca de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n ficio <hi>lib 3. cap. 30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this ground it is that <hi>Seneca</hi> (a wiſe man, Tutor to an Emperor, and one that well underſtood what he wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) breaks forth into that paſſionate interrogation, <hi>Quid omnia poſſidentibus deeſt? ille qui verum dicat.</hi> What thing only do they want which poſſeſs all things? Even (anſwers he) a perſon that will give them honeſt Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And therefore the Lord Chancellour <hi>Bacon</hi> (among many other his excellent Counſels to the late Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi>) urgeth this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing document to him with a warmer zeal then ordinary.<note place="margin">Cabala of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters fol. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> In reſpect of the King your Maſter (ſaith he) you muſt be very wary that you give him true information, and if the matter concern him in his government, that you do not flatter him; if you do, you are as great a Traytor to him, in the Court of Heaven, as he that drawes his Sword againſt him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This grievance of our hath been repreſented to his Majeſty under the pretence and umbrages of Royal Prerogative (which in truth he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to maintain) and of publique Emolument and advantage (which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are the moſt glorious Objects of Royal prudence). With theſe and the like Blandiſhments Sir this Chryſtal Fountain of Juſtice hath been poyſon'd and contaminated. This is the Coloquintida with which ſo unſpeakable a ſweetneſs hath been imbittered, theſe are the Paintings with which ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed an Advice hath been ſophiſticated. But let me tell you Sir, if in the ſequel of this diſcourſe I ſhall not clearly wipe off all theſe Varniſhes and falſe colours, and effectively prove this advice to be as miſchievous to his Sacred Majeſty as his people, I ſhall think I have very meanly acquitted my ſelf in this buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I hope I ſhall not be thought to reflect herein, upon any perſon whatſoever, any farther then his own Conſcience may ſcourge him in this particular. And I know there be many great and illuſtrious Hero's near his Majeſty, (to whoſe ſervice I could willingly ſacrifice an hundred lives had I them) that do abominate ſo pernicious a Councel. 'Tis not for me raſhly to touch heads irradicated with the Beams of Royal favour: For my part I meddle not with the perſon, but with the Advice abſtracted, <hi>Amo hominem, odi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> is a good Rule</p>
            <p>And I praiſe God and the King, we live not now in an Age wherein it is more hazardous to diſcover, an evil action, than to commit it, or wherein the juſtly accuſed ſhall take Revenge of the juſt Accuſer.</p>
            <p>Neither would I be underſtood here to erect my ſelf into an Advocate for the Trade and miſtery of <hi>Banking,</hi> A God's name where the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuries of thoſe people are by the King found outragious and illegal, let them be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and reduced to juſt moderations. All that I contend for is, that the Bankers (whoſe concernments are now apparently become ours) may by O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the Exchequer be enabled to ſatisfy their juſt debts to their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that ſo the good and bad, the nocent and innocent may not thus be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed together in one and the ſame common Ruine.</p>
            <p>Sir, let us not flatter our ſelves, poſterity will aſſuredly diſcourſe our Actions, with the ſame freedome that we do thoſe of our Anceſtors.<note place="margin">Annalium lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irriden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt eorum ſocordia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi>) <hi>qui preſenti potentia credunt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingui poſſe ſequentis aevi memoriam.</hi> The improvidence of thoſe perſons (ſaith he) is ridiculous, who think by preſent power to extinguiſh the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of future Ages. No this cannot be, the voluminous Hiſtories of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which we dayly read and handle, prove this project altogether idle and impracticable. Certainly there abides in mankind an immortal principle, a Ray of the Divinity which natrually inclineth us to a deſire of Glory, and to have our names guilded to all Ages in the eternal Records of Far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>Now Sir becauſe you ſhall ſee with what Candor and fairneſs I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
<pb facs="tcp:51796:4"/>ſecute this Argument, I ſhall deduce my following Obſervations from the wiſeſt Hiſtorians and Stateſmen, from the greateſt and moſt glorious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that the world hath at any time afforded, from juſtictaries of the moſt profound Learning, and chaſteſt integrity, nay from bodies of the wiſeſt men of this and other nations in conjunction, from Parliaments and their Determinations remaining with us upon Record,<note place="margin">Bacons Eſſay of Councel. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Cortile:</hi> Lipſis Epiſtola ad porit. <hi>Ad Nicoclem.</hi>
               </note> and (becauſe I would take off all imaginable objection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the credit of my Authors) I ſhall produce only ſuch which have long ſince departed this liſe, which for that reaſon (as a wiſe King was uſed to ſay) were the moſt faithful Councellors. Such as theſe (as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> tells) cannot be daunted with fear, or blinded with affection, or corrupted with preferments.</p>
            <p>Theſe have indeed the character of true Councellors,<note place="margin">Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llanus de Officio Regis <hi>Lio. 1. cap. 55.</hi>
               </note> which is, <hi>Ut non modo ne quid fa ſi dicere audeant, ſed etiam ne quid veri non audeant,</hi> that they will neither dare to tell a falſity, or conceal a truth.</p>
            <p>That would rather (as <hi>Seneca</hi> tells <hi>Nero</hi>) <hi>Veris offendere quam placere adulando.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De elem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntia Lib. 2. cap. 2.</note> Offend by telling Truth, then pleaſe by deſtructive adulations and flattery. And laſtly, ſuch which <hi>Demetreus Phalereus</hi> adviſed King <hi>Ptolomy</hi> to converſe with often;<note place="margin">Stobeus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone 46.</note> becauſe quoth he, <hi>ibi quae amici monere non audeant Reges, ea ſacile omnia poſſint reperire.</hi> There Kings may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover thoſe matters themſelves, which poſſibly their beſt friends ſometimes dare not adviſe them to.</p>
            <p>Sir, I fear I have treſpaſt too far upon your patience by way of Letter already, I ſhall therefore for your farther ſatisfaction in all theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars refer you to the enſuing diſcourſe, deteining you here no longer then while I ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Faithful friend and Servant</hi> Sma. Ro.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Introduction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kings Debt to the <hi>Bankers,</hi> with the miſerable conſequences thereof, hath now (for little leſs then three years together) exerciſed the world with matter, not only of diſcourſe, but aſtoniſhment For indeed who will not be ſtartled to ſee the common Faith of a Nation violated, and a forcible breach made upon all that may be card Religious and binding, and this alſo in great meaſure, to the Ruine of Orphans and Widows, and ſeveral, even of thoſe who with unwearied conſtancy reſiſted unto blood, and loſs of whatſoever was dear unto them in defence of the Crown of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> I ſhall not here lanch out into the ſtory of particular caſes, that Theme will be infinite, and of force to endue ſtones with ſpeech, and (by a contrariety of Miracle) to overwhelme the moſt eloquent with ſilence.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but I have already Arreſted my Reader with frequent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſements, and he is by this time impatient to know what may be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all theſe words? and wherefore a private paſſenger in the Ship of the Common-wealth, ſhould in this manner concern himſelf in the ſayling thereof?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Firſt that every Subject is obliged to vindicate, and propugne the Honour and Innocency of his Soveraign; and to caſt the Envies and Malignancy of Peſtilent Councels, upon the Donors and contrivers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and perhaps this duty could never be more ſeaſonably exerted then in this preſent Caſe. For I ſhould be ſorry that this Adviſor (as a perſon of great Honour and worth, ſaid not long ſince, of one of them openly) ſhould like a Rabbit ſtart out of his Borough, and look about him, and then run in
<pb facs="tcp:51796:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>again, and hide himſelf, and think no body obſerv'd him. Certainly he is no good Miniſter or Servant that will throw the odium of his own evil actions upon his Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Secondly that all men are interreſſed in the ſafety of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel they are imbarqut in, though all ought not to preſide at the Helme: And pernicious Advices (like the falcities of the Turkiſh Alchoran) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes gain ſtrength by the prohibitions of diſputing them. I know I ſhall be thought to broach a Paradox, if I ſhould affirm that ſome moderate freedomes of this nature, have been ſometimes Characters and marks of the happieſt and moſt peaceable Ages of the world; and yet if this aſſertion be not in ſome meaſure true,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and troubles</note> we muſt abandon faith to all Hiſtory: For (as the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> well notes) ſuch Liberties give vent and diſcharge often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to popular diſcontentments, and beſides the Prince is hereby inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in what part the Subject is pincht and griev'd, when perhaps he ſhall attain this information no other way. And therefore <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> (one of the happieſt and greateſt Prince it may be that the Sun ever ſaw) when he was told at any time,<note place="margin">Eutropius lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> that even his own perſon, and his Edicts were too boldy diſcourſt of in <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Boterus de poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> lib. 7. c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Quod in Civitate libera, linguas quoque civium liberas eſſe oportere.</hi> That in a free City, the Citizens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ought alſo to be free. And this candid profeſſion of his, might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be no mean ingredient in the compoſition of his own felicities. <hi>Thua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> writing to the great <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thuani Epiſtola ante Hiſtoriam ſuam ad Hen. <hi>4.</hi> Franciae.</note> unto other Laudatives of that Princes Reign, adds this, as none of the meaneſt. <hi>Ea eſt Domine rarae tuorum temporum faelieitas</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in quibus unicui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſentire quae velit, &amp; quae ſentiat eloqui licet.</hi> Such (Great Sir) is the rare happineſs of your times, that in them every man may think what he pleaſeth, and ſpeak what he thinketh And of the ſame complexion was that ſerene Age, in which the excellent Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> Reign'd, as <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> (who was then living) affirms from whom the ſaid <hi>Thuanus</hi> ſeems to have borrowed the very individual words before recited.<note place="margin">Taciti Hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> in proemio.</note> I write not this in countenance of clamour, and ſcurrilities againſt thoſe things which I have alwayes reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced and held ſacred; but under favour, in our preſent caſe, where all nature is big, and in travail to be delivered of ſpeech, I hope her voice ſhall not be ſtifled and ſuppreſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall redargue this Objector, with that principle (which the Adviſers of this calamity have thought ſo puiſſant) <hi>I</hi> mean exigences, and invincible neceſſity, a neceſſity of no ordinary nature neither, but of near allyance to that thing which we proverbially ſay breaks through ſtone walls, that in hard winterly weather infuſeth boldneſs even into Brutes, that alſo where nature languiſheth, and the means wherewith ſhe ſhould be ſupported are unjuſtly ſubſtracted from her. The old Comicke ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:51796:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>well <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>pecunia Anima, &amp; ſanguis eſt morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus.</hi> Money is the liſe and blood of mankind. To deprive a man wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully then of that little money which he poſſeſſeth, what is it but to deprive him of his blood, yea of his life? I know the great and opulent men of the world cannot deſcend ſo low as to conceive how much it importeth poor men and their Families to be in a moment diſpoild of all their ſubſiſtence, and to be bereav'd perhaps of a few poor weather-beaten, water-drencht Reliques, which they had reſcued out of the wrecks of their Fortunes in the late dreadful ſtorm of Rebellion, but yet they may pleaſe to believe, that we are as much paind with the preſſures of our Little fortunes, as they are with thoſe of their great ones. I ſpeak this not out of any pride I take in comparing great things with ſmall, but only to diſpoſe my Reader to a favourable conſtruction of my words, if my zeal may ſeem to tranſport me beyond the bounds of decency.</p>
            <p>Laſtly I am not altogether without hope, but that ſomething poſſibly may happen to be ſaid in this Scribble, that may conduce to the healing up this wound again. For the Phyſitians have a good Aphoriſm, <hi>Primus gradus ſanitatis, eſt noviſſe morbum.</hi> The firſt degree of health is to know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>I know ſome men are apt enough to alledge, that this caſe is the leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, becauſe but a few perſons are therein concerned. In this place I ſhall ſay no more, but that this Aſſertion is a great miſtake. For firſt, out Money being expended for the defence of the Kingdome, it was laid out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the publick utility, and certainly it will be very diſproportionable that the common advantage ſhould be maintained by a private contribution, and upon this reaſon <hi>a perſon of great Honour and prudence</hi> not long ſince in an Audience of the whole Kindome doubted not to affirm, <hi>That this concern was little leſs then national</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe this may ſeem to many to be but a precarious and begging Argument, and being founded upon a conſideration of ſervice and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſome time ſince done, may (in this ungrateful Age) prove but of mean regard. I will therefore Secondly, demonſtrate this matter to be of Epidemical concernment in point of continuing and permanent intereſt: In order to this, I will ſuppoſe that the King owes a Banker 1000 <hi>l.</hi> this Banker owes me the like ſumm, I ow as much to a third, be to a fourth, and ſo in <hi>infinitum,</hi> and the Banker, my ſelf, and the third perſon, have little elſe to ſatisfie our Creditors than this 1000 <hi>l.</hi> which is owing ſeverally to us. (which caſe may be well ſuppoſed to have hapned ſince the ſtop of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer) In this caſe then I ſay, it will be moſt evident, that if the King never payeth the Banker, the Banker can never pay me, or I the third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or he the fourth, ſo that by a neceſſary chain of conſequences, the <hi>4th.</hi> perſon and his Creditors in <hi>infinitum,</hi> are as much grieved by the King's
<pb facs="tcp:51796:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>non-payment of the Banker, as I may ſelf, who am the Bankers immediate Credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or. For as (I ſaid before) money is the blood of the Body Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and we know if the circu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at on thereof be ſtopt in one Member, that blood can ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er be tranſmitted to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ouring Vein, and thereupon not only that part, but the whole body in fine becomes Feavouriſh and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhant. The like may be ſaid of Rents, Executorſhips, Legacies, &amp;c. And I doubt not but every man's conſideration, and the particular intereſts of moſt perſons, will furniſh them with infinite inſtances of like nature, in a very little time.</p>
            <p>But if this Reaſon prove not ſufficiently praevalent in this matter, I muſt be inforc'd to go a ſtep higher, and to ſay, Thirdly, That if this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fall out to be an invaſion of property (as I think I ſhall anon prove it is) then I ſay every individual perſon will be interreſſed in the Fate of this Cauſe.<note place="margin">The Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the Bankers have been computed to a number, little inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this. The Creditors by conſequence are far more.</note> For by the ſame reaſon that the Rights of Ten thouſand men may be violated, the Rights of Twenty thouſand men may, and ſo in <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum.</hi> And I think it is obvious to every man, that the publique and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Cares, and wiſdome of this State have been extended in point of redreſſing Grievances, not only to bodies of men, in number much inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to ours; but oftentimes even to particular perſons, where the preſures have been enormous.</p>
            <p>This is the Anſwer I ſhall give to this Allegation at preſent, in the ſequel of this diſcourſe, very probably I may add more.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premis'd, <hi>I</hi> ſhall now forthwith addreſs my ſelf to the main buſineſs. In the Argument whereof I ſhall obſerve theſe Gradations, or ſteps.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhortly put the eaſe (as it now ſtands) between the King and the Bankers.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, <hi>I</hi> ſhall prove that by this Councel of ſtopping payments in the Exchequer, the Subjects property is invaded at Common Law.</item>
               <item>3. Thirdly, that hereby it is invaded contray to the Statute Law.</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, that this Councel is expreſly contray to his Majeſties gracious promiſes and Declarations. Printed and promulgated by His own eſpecial command.</item>
               <item>5. Fifthly, I ſhall at large anſwer the grand Objection of neceſſity, and National danger (ſuppoſing too our fears to be at that time juſt) And ſhall prove by ſundry Records and otherwiſe that the Subjects property is not violable but by his own conſent, in caſes of far greater National Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then this was. <hi>I</hi> ſhall anſwer, the Rapines of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and <hi>3d.</hi> (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would take up this Objection by the Roots) I ſhall then ſhew what courſes the Law hath provided for preſervation of the Kingdome, where the danger is inſtant and cannot ſtay for a Parliament.</item>
               <item>6. Sixthly <hi>I</hi> ſhall prove that this Councel is contray to the Pollicies
<pb facs="tcp:51796:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>hitherto uſed by the wiſeſt Forreign States of the World, in far greater Exigencies then ours. I ſhall anſwer the Objection of ſome Princes not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paying Money lent them by their Subjects, to retain them in better Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</item>
               <item>7. Seventhly, I ſhall prove this Councel to be contrary to common Reaſon, and in ſome reſpects to violate the Rules of Humanity. That it is pernicious to the credit of his Majeſties Exchequer. Then I ſhall truly ſtate the caſe between <hi>Phillip</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and the Bankers of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and ſhall prove that caſe eſſentially different from ours.</item>
               <item>And Laſtly, ſhall frame a Concluſion upon the whole matter.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 1.</hi> The Caſe put between the King and the Bankers.</head>
               <p>I think it is now evident enough to every man that underſtands any thing, that the concernment of the Bankers is now become the concernment of their Creditors, and that both their intereſts are common, and ſo inſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably twiſted together, that the proſperity of the latter, will depend alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon the Fate of the former. Inſomuch that if the Banker never receive his debt, I do not in probability ſee how he will be able to ſatisfie his Creditor: we are therefore by invincible neceſſity obliged to maintain the right of the Banker, and in order thereunto I will now put his Caſe, which in ſhort is no more but this.</p>
               <p>A Banker lends to the King an hundred thouſand pounds, more or leſs; this money is ſecured to the ſaid Banker upon the Cuſtomes, or any other Branch of the King's Revenues, &amp;c. by Order Regiſtred in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or by Talley of Loane, or both, and then the King (upon the War-like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of our neighbour Princes and States) is adviſed to make ſtop of all payments out of the Exchequer, which is executed accordingly; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this Councel executed the Subjects property be invaded? and I clearly conceive it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 2.</hi> That by this Councel of ſtopping Payments out of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> the Subject, prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is in vaded at Common Law.</head>
               <p>IT is an Eſſential principle of the Law of this Realine. That the Subject hath an undoubted property in his Goods and Poſſeſſions. Otherwiſe there ſhall remain no more induſtry, no more Juſtice, no more valour, for who will labour? who will hazzard his perſon in he day of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for that which is not his own? How can the Subject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y any Act of Boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate himſelf with his Soveraign? Neither was this Right of propriety in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc there by any Charter or Edict of Princes, but was the old Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Law,<note place="margin">Lambards Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaion, Forteſ. de laudibus Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Angliae. cap. <hi>17.</hi> Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales <hi>Origines Jurid ciales.</hi> Inſinite Autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rities there quo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to prove this, See there Fol. <hi>5.6.</hi>
                  </note> ſpringing from the Original, Frame, and firſt Architecture of the Kingdome. There were manifeſt Footſteps of this Law in the Brit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh, Roman, Saxon and Daniſh Governments here, nay it was of that vigour and puiſſance to ſurvive even the very Norman Conqueſt. To prove which I ſhall crave leave to produce this following ſhort memorable Record. <hi>One</hi> Shirboorn <hi>a Saxon at the time of the Conqueſt, being ſeized of a Caſtle and Lands in</hi> Norfolke, William <hi>the Conquerer gave the ſame to one</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren <hi>a Norman, of principal Quality;</hi> Shirboorn <hi>dying, his Heir ſhewed to the Conquerour that he was his Subject, and that he ought to Inherit the ſaid Caſtle and Land, by vertue of that Law which he himſelf had eſtabliſht in</hi> England. In this Caſe the Conquerour gave Judgement for <hi>Shirboorn</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Warren,</hi> and pronounc'd his own former gift void. See for this <hi>Cambden</hi> in his Deſcription of <hi>Norfolk.</hi> And Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> Rep. 41, a. The Caſe of <hi>Taniſtry.</hi> And there it is ſaid by Judge <hi>Calthrop,</hi> that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had ſeen an Authentique Copy of this Judgement.</p>
               <p>For indeed the Common Law is not more ſolicitous of any one thing then to preſerve the property of the Subject from the inundation of the Prerogative. And therefore where a cuſtome is to pay Toll for all Cattle that ſhall be driven over a common Bridge, this Cuſtome ſhall bind the Subject but not the King; but where a Cuſtome is to pay Toll for all Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle that ſhall be driven over a mans private Freehold, there the Cuſtome ſhall prevail againſt the Prerogative, and what's the Reaſon? why, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law will not allow the King to invade the Subjects Inheritance and Property without conſent and compenſation. For this ſee the expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s book of 46 of <hi>Ed,</hi> 3. cited in <hi>Plowden</hi> 236. <hi>a.</hi> The Lord <hi>Barkley's</hi> caſe. Many other caſes of this nature are there recited, and in other Books of our Law, which for brevity I for bear to mention.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>To come then to the Hinge upon which this point turns. I do lay this down for an indiſputeable ground. That the Law of the Court of <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer</hi> is the univerſal Law of this Land, and ſo is <hi>Plowden</hi> 320. <hi>b.</hi> and 321. <hi>b.</hi> The caſe of <hi>Mines,</hi> and <hi>Cooks 2d Report</hi> 16. <hi>b. Lanes</hi> caſe adjudg'd. Now then by the Law of the Exchequer, when the King hath charged himſelf to the Subject by Talley and liberate (as in our caſe) to pay a ſumme of money out of his Cuſtomes or any other branch of his Revenue, and his Collector hath received this Revenew; this money though at firſt it appertains in property to the King, yet as ſoon as ever the Kings Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor comes to this Collector, and ſhewes him his Talley and Liberate, and demands payment accordingly, the property of this money (to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the Debt) by meer operation of Law, is transfer'd out of the King into the Collector or Receiver, and in an inſtant becomes the proper and perſonal Money of the ſaid Collector, or Receiver; in reſpect of his charge over to the party. And ſo it is clearly affirmed by all the Judges of both Benches <hi>Plowden</hi> 186. <hi>a.</hi> Lord <hi>Darcyes</hi> caſe.</p>
               <p>And therefore if the King grant a ſumm of money to <hi>I. S.</hi> to be received out of his Cuſtoms of <hi>London,</hi> I ſay that by the delivery of the Talley Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate, and aſſets in the hands of the Cuſtomer, the Cuſtomer is become a Debtor to <hi>I. S.</hi> and he may bring his Action of Debt upon this matter againſt the Cuſtomer. <hi>Coke's</hi> 4 <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> 116. <hi>F. N. B</hi> 121. <hi>F.</hi> 21. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Fitzh. Debt</hi> 43.27. <hi>H.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Fitzh. Bar.</hi> 314. <hi>Brook Talley d'Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</hi> 1.37. <hi>H.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Brooke ibid.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Nay in ſuch caſe if the Receiver dye, the Action will lye againſt his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutor. And therefore where the King had granted a Fee by Patent to the Clercke of the Parliament to be received out of the profits of the Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par, and the Clercke of the Hanapar dyed, yet adjudged that debt would well lye againſt his Executor, becauſe ſo much of the Kings money was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in property in the hands of the Teſtator, and yet here was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, privity in word, ſuit or Execution of Law between the King and Teſta or, or Executor, 2. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.8. <hi>b. &amp;c. Fitzh. Bar.</hi> 124. <hi>Ploxden</hi> 36. <hi>b.</hi> and 186. <hi>a.</hi> So if the King aſſign Talleys upon the Diſmes (gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him by Parliament) to his Creditors, and they ſhew them to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors of the Diſmes, the King is hereby diſcharged, and the Collecto s are charg'd, and the King cannot pardon the Collectors, or the Clergy which granted the Diſmes. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.8. <hi>a. Brook Charter de pardon,</hi> 37. Nay ſo careful is the Law of the Subjects property in ſuch caſe, that if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a like grant of the Diſms, the King ſhould dye, yet the Collectors are chargeable to the King's Grantee and not to his Succeſſor. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.8. <hi>a. per omnes Justitiaries, Brooke Quinzime</hi> 7. <hi>Fitzh. Quinzime.</hi> 2. <hi>Brook Talley d' Exchequer,</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> Now if any man ſhall ſay to me. Sir you have abundantly prov'd the
<pb facs="tcp:51796:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtopping of the Exchequer, to be an invaſion of Property as to the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Cuſtomer, and the like by the Common Law, but nothing at all as to the Banker or his Creditor, which was the poſition you undertook to maintain.</p>
               <p>To this Objection, I give this plain Anſwer. <hi>That the ſtop of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer to the Collectors, Cuſtomers, &amp;c. is by inevitable conſequence a ſtop to the Bankers and their Crediors, (and ſo likewiſe their property viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) becauſe by this Obſtruction the Collector, &amp;c. is diſabled to ſatisfy the Banker, and the Banker his Creditor, and that Creditor his Creditor, and ſo in an infinite rotation throughout the Kingdom: juſt as a wrongful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheritance of the Grandfather, is an injury to the Father, and Son, and ſo to all their Line in ſucceſſion to the worlds end. Or (becauſe this is the Hinge of the caſe as to the Common Law, and I would make it plain) I will ſuppoſe twenty Mills to be built upon one River, each of them in ſequence one below the other, a perſon comes and damms up this River, or diverts the current thereof into a new Channel; I do ſay that by this diverſion or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Stream the 20th Mill is injured as well as the first, becauſe (if there were no Impediment) that water which comes to the first Mill would at the long run arrive to the twentieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſo plain a caſe I need not make any Application, or indeed uſe any farther Argument as to the Common law-part of this diſcourſe. I ſhall therefore cite but one other caſe, and that a far ſtronger one then ours, and then diſcharge my ſelf of this Section.</p>
               <p>The Caſe is <hi>Mich.</hi> 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>Fol.</hi> 3. <hi>b.</hi> and abridg'd by <hi>Fitzherbert Barr.</hi> 122. <hi>Touts les Juſtices fueront al</hi> White Fryers <hi>pur lour Fees, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith the Book) All the Judges were aſſembled at <hi>White Fryars</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult about the payment of their Salleries which were behind. And their Caſe was this. By a Statute made 18. <hi>Hen</hi> 6. it is Enacted that the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſhall pay the Judges their Salleries, out of the firſt Moneys ariſing out of the Cuſtomes of <hi>London.</hi> And then <hi>Richard</hi> the third grants Licenſe to certain Merchants to carry Wools, and to retain the Cuſtoms thereof in their own hands (which was as it were a little diminutive ſtopping of the Exchequer as to the Iudges in this Caſe) And the queſtion was whether the Cuſtomers ſhall be chargeable to the Judges for thoſe reteinments of the Merchants, and after mature debate, Reſolved by them all, That the Cuſtomers were chargeable even for thoſe recemments, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to their hands; and in the end of that caſe, it is ſaid, that the Judges deſign'd each of them to bring his Action againſt the Cuſtomers, which they perceiving, they forthwith agreed with the Judges to pay them their galleries.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Now any man that ſhall well conſider this caſe will find the Reaſon thereof to be, becauſe though the King had granted the Priveledge of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining the Cuſtomes to theſe Merchants, yet in contemplation of Law, the Cuſtomers did ſtill actually receive thoſe Cuſtomes, and ſo were chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Judges (like the caſe I put before of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.8. <hi>a.</hi> where the King remitred the Diſmes to the Collector, or Clergy) and the rather in this caſe, becauſe this private Licenſe of the Kings ſhall not prevail over an act of Parhament, which had ſecured unto them their Salaries out of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, which leads me to the next poſition which I have propoſed to aſſert, which is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 3.</hi> That by this Councel of ſtopping Payments in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, the Subjects Property is invaded againſt Statute-Law.</head>
               <p>OUr Books tell us (and not without Reaſon) That the Parliament <hi>Eſt un Court de treſgrand honor &amp; juſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plowden 398.</hi> b Earle of Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſters caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>de que nul doyt imaginer choſe diſhonourable,</hi> is a Court of thrice great Honour, and Juſtice, of which no man may preſume to think a diſhonourable thing. And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſuppoſe (ſaith the Lord Chance lour <hi>Forteſcue</hi>) that Statute Laws carry with them no mean force as well as Wiſdome. <hi>Dum non unius aut centum folum conſultorum prudentia, ſed pluſquam trecentorum electorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Forteſcue de laudebus legum Angliae. ca. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When they are the reſults not of the prudence of one or two or three hundred only of the Select men of the Kingdome, but of a far greater number. In this Orbe. the King like the Sun ſhines in the Exaltation of Majeſty and grandeur, invironed by the illuſtrious members of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and from the conjunction of this great and leſſer lights, propitious and refreſhing influences are derived to the whole Kingdome.<note place="margin">Hobart <hi>256.</hi> Duncombs caſe. <hi>21</hi> Hen. <hi>7.</hi> a per Vavaſor.</note> The Acts of this Court are the higheſt ſecurities this Nation can give, and ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curityes that do in themſelves comprehend the univerſal conſent of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in this Realme, as well future as preſent.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not here inſiſt upon the Grand Charter, or upon any other Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works of propriety of that nature (though poſſibly pertinent enough to my purpoſe) but ſhall rather chooſe at preſent to apply my ſelf to a Statute. Law of much freſher date and memory, and deſign'd for the Relief of this very particular caſe. And that is the Statute of 190 of his now Majeſty, Chap. 12. which I ſhall recite (ſo far as it concerns my purpoſe) <hi>verbatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereas it hath been found by experience upon the late Act for Twelve hundred and fifty thouſand pounds, made at</hi> Oxford, <hi>and other Acts of Parliament ſince that time, that the power of Aſſigning of Orders in the</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer <hi>upon thoſe Acts, without Revocation, hath been of great uſe and advantage to the perſons concerned in them, and to the Trade of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and given great Credit to His Majeſties Exchequer: Be it Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and it is hereby Enacted by the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, by and with the Advice and Conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled,</hi> That every perſon <hi>or perſons, Native or Forreigner, Bodies Politique or Corporate,</hi> to whom any Moneys ſhall be due in your Majeſties <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and ſhall have any Order Regiſtred in the Office of the Auditor of the Receipt, for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof out of any branch of your Majeſties Revenue; <hi>That ſuch perſon or perſons, Native or Forreigner, Bodies Politique, or Corporate, their Succeſſors, Executors, Adminiſtrators or Aſſigns, reſpectively, by Endorſement of their Order,</hi> may Aſſign <hi>and transfer</hi> their Right, Title, Intereſt and Benefic of ſuch Order, <hi>or any part thereof, to any other; which being notified in the Office of the Auditor of the Receipt aforeſaid, and an Entry and Memorial thereof alſo made in the Book of Regiſtry aforeſaid for ſuch Orders (which the Officers ſhall on requeſt accordingly make) ſhall Entitle ſuch Aſſignee, his Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſort reſpectively, to the benefit thereof, and payment thereon.</hi> Now it will be plain to any man that ſhall conſider this Statute, that the Parliament doth therein admit an unqueſtionable duty of the Mony, to the Lenders in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> (for ſo are the words, Every perſon to whom any mony ſhal be due in your Majeſties Exchequer &amp;c.) and the makers of this Act, could never mean that nothing ſhould be transferd to the Aſſignee: For indeed all the Powers of the Univerſe can never make me Donor of that which never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to me, nor I never had in me to give, And therefore this money muſt firſt of neceſſity veſt in my ſelf in point of property,<note place="margin">Nit dat quod non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet</note> before I can transfer it to another perſon, ſo then if this Law ſecure this money to my Aſſignee, <hi>a multo fortiori</hi> to my ſelf. Now that this Statute ſecures this money to my Aſſignee, I ſhall prove by three unanſwerable reaſons (as I ſuppoſe) all drawn out of the Bowels of this very Law it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Inducements of this Statute appear in the preamble thereof to be. Advantage to the perſons concern'd. To the Trade of the Kingdome, and alſo great credit to the Exchequer. Therefore the makers of this Law could never deſign a transferring of the husk or ſhell only, that is of the Order or Paper, but even of the fruit it ſelf, I mean the money in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> for that is it which carryes the Advantage, the Trade, and the credit with it and not the Order or writings as many of us find by wofull Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Secondly, there is no man doubts but that the moneys lent upon the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. for 1250000 <hi>l.</hi> And upon the Pole-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Bill 18. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. And upon the Act of 19. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. for 1256000 <hi>l.</hi> were unqueſtionably ſecured to the Aſſignees of the Lenders by thoſe ſeveral Acts; why then I ſay that all moneys ſince that time Lent into the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> &amp; charg'd upon any branch of the King's Revenue, are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecur'd to them by this Act, and that not only firſt becauſe this Act in the preamble thereof refers expreſly to thoſe other Acts; But Secondly, (then which I think nothing can be plainer) becauſe the moneys ſecured by this Act to the Aſſignees are ſecured with almoſt all the ſame numerical, iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical words, with which the moneys lent upon the three other Acts are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured: And this will be obvious to any perſon that ſhall curiouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare all theſe Acts together, to the which for brevity ſake I am inforc't to refer my Reader.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this Act declares in expreſs terms that the Aſſignees of ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for money due in the Exchequer, their Executors Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes in <hi>infinitum</hi> ſhall be Entituled <hi>To the Benefit of ſuch Orders, and Payment thereon,</hi> which words being ſo plain, that he that runs may read, and wrote as it were with a Beame of the Sun, I think there can be no place left for farther cavil or ſubterfuge in this matter.</p>
               <p>I had almoſt forgot to obſerve that this Law (the King being therein concerned) is a general Act of Parliament,<note place="margin">Cooks 4th. Rep. <hi>77.</hi> a. Hollands Caſe. Plowd. Lord <hi>Barkley</hi>'s caſe, ibid. Wim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhes caſe.</note> of the which not only the Judges, but even every individual Subject of this Kingdome ought to take knowledge of courſe; for as the inferiour Members (ſaith the Book) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſtrange themſelves from the actions and paſſions of the head, no more can any Subject be a ſtranger to the concernments of his Sovereign. This I would add to thoſe Anſwers I gave before to the Objection, that this affair was private, and that few perſons were concernd in the preſent Caſe of the Bankers and their Creditors, now I proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 4.</hi> That this Counſel of ſtopping up the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> is expreſly contrary to His Majeſties gracious promiſes, and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations Printed and publiſh't by His own eſpecial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</head>
               <p>MY deſign all along in this diſcourſe being to diſcover the peſtilence and miſchief of this Councel, in relation as well to his Majeſty as his people. I cannot with better advantage diſcharge my ſelf of the Province I have undertaken in this Section, and manifeſt how unhandſomly his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath been treated by this Adviſer, then by conſidering a while the ſanctimony of promiſes among Princes.</p>
               <p>Nothing then I ſay is more ſacred or tremendous among Princes then their publik Faiths and Declarations. This the Emperour <hi>Tiberius</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood well when he ſaid <hi>Caeteris mortalibus in eo ſtant concilia quod ſibi conducere putant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tacit. Ann. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>principum vero, &amp;c.</hi> Inferiour perſons may order their Councels, as they beſt ſort with their advantages, but the condition of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates is different, whoſe actions are principally to be directed to Fame and Glory.<note place="margin">Cambden and Baker vita Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zab. Regina.</note> And for this reaſon Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her private Letters to K <hi>James,</hi> was uſed to admoniſh him that a Prince muſt be ſuch a lover of Truth, that more credit may be given to his bare Word, than to anothers Oath.</p>
               <p>And we know that the man after God's own heart, and a King too, writes, <hi>He that promiſeth to his Neighbour, and diſappointeth him not, though it were to his own hindrance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</note> I do never without Admiration think of that great ſaying of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> Emperour, when he was preſt to break his word with <hi>Luther,</hi> for his ſafe return from <hi>Wormes. Fides rerum promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum</hi> (quoth he) <hi>etſi toto mundo exulet tamen apud imperatorem eam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtere oportet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Xenocarus vita Caroli <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> Though the faith of promiſes ſhould be baniſht out of the world, yet it ought alway to find Sanctuary in an Emperours breaſt. And to this virtue even <hi>Campanella</hi> the Jeſuite doth vigorouſly adviſe <hi>Phil.</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spaniſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy c. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> for nothing ſaith he doth more effectually oblige the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Prince then fidelity of promiſes. By this means (continues he) <hi>Alexander Farneſe</hi> Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> contain'd the Netherland in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero 1 Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic.</note> whereas the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> by the contrary courſe loſt them. And this will not ſeem ſtrange to a man that ſhall conſider, that <hi>ſides</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) <hi>eſt juſticia fundamentum.</hi> Faith is the Foundation
<pb facs="tcp:51796:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon which Juſtice is built,<note place="margin">Boterus de poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Juſtitia vero nulla eſſe poteſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Boterus</hi>) <hi>niſi conventionum fuerit, &amp; promiſſorum certa fides, ac neceſsaria ſolutio rerum creditarum.</hi> But there can be no Juſtice without performance of promiſes, and fair ſatisfaction of Debts. And this moſt of all in the caſe of Princes,<note place="margin">De Repu. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> Forteſcue c. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> for (as <hi>Bodine</hi> affirms) <hi>Cum ſummus Princeps mutuae fidei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter privatos ac Legum omnium ulicr &amp; vindex eſt, quanto magis datam a ſe fidem ac promiſſa ſervare tenetur.</hi> For when a Prince is himſelf to avenge the violations of Faith and Lawes among his Subjects, how much more then ought he himſelf to obſerve his own Faith and Promiſes: And in this very point he voucheth there a judgement of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and a little after adds, <hi>Itaque in judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis cum Fides principis agitur, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore ſaith he, when the Faith of a Prince happens to be debated in Judicature, we are rather to conſult the benefit of the Subject, and in ſuch caſe to treat the Prince more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely.</p>
               <p>And this indeed is no more then what the municipal Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome warrant, which ſay,<note place="margin">Cooks <hi>11.</hi> Rep. Magdalen Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge caſe.</note> that the Grants of the King are to be Expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded liberally, and withal imaginable favour to the Subject, for the Honour and Dignity of the King, as alſo that the King's <hi>Teſte meipſo is Recordum Suparlativum,</hi> a Record of the higheſt puiſſance and grandeur. I have the more largely here dilated upon this Subject, that I might with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter clearneſs diſcloſe the Poyſon of this Advice, it being ſo apparently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Majeſties moſt gracious Promiſes and Declarations Printed and promulgated by his own immediate Order, and particularly that of the <hi>18th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1667 (of the which ſeveral Copies then Printed were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by my ſelf and others, as the higheſt Muniments and Securities for our Monies in the Bankers hands.)</p>
               <p>This is ſtiled <hi>His Majeſties Declaration to all his loving Subjects to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve inviolably the Securities by him given for moneys,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, in the end of this Treatiſe</note> 
                  <hi>and the due courſe of payments thereon in the Receipt of the Exchequer.</hi> In this Declaration (about the middle) theſe very numerical wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds following are inſerted. <hi>And that we will not upon any occaſion whatſoever, permit or ſuffer any Alteration, Anticipation, or Interruption to be made of our ſaid Subjects</hi> (that is, of the Bankers) <hi>Securities, but that they ſhall from time to time receive the moneys ſo ſecured unto them</hi> (<hi>upon ſeveral branches of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Revenue, and other late Acts of Parliament</hi> ſaith the preamble) <hi>in the ſame courſe and method, as they were charged and ought to be ſatisfied.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after follow theſe remarkable words, <hi>which Reſolution we</hi> ſhall <hi>likewiſe hold firm and ſacred in all</hi> Future <hi>Aſſignments and Securities</hi> to be <hi>by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s granted upon any</hi> Other <hi>advance of money by any of our Subjects</hi> (note this is general) <hi>upon any</hi> Futute <hi>Occaſion for Our ſervice. And we cannot doubt upon the Publiſhing this Our</hi> Royal Word <hi>and Declaration of
<pb facs="tcp:51796:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Our</hi> Sincere Intention, <hi>but that all reaſonable perſons will reſt ſatisfied, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would fain know what more adaequate or preventive words could have been deviſed by the Wit or Providence of men and Angels to have ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled ſo great a calamity in the Birth.</p>
               <p>Neither will it be an Obſervation perhaps altogether immaterial and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, that in the very next Seſſion of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>October</hi> immediately following the Statute of the <hi>19th.</hi> of his now Majeſty, <hi>cap.</hi> 12. (which I have before recited) was made, as it were in Buttreſs and ſupport of this Royal Edict and Declaration.</p>
               <p>Theſe things ſtanding thus as I have repreſented them, however the King's Honour and Juſtice (like a Rock of Diamonds) remains ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penetrable, neither is his Sacred Majeſty in this caſe any more to be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the breaches of fidelity, then the chaſt <hi>Lucretia</hi> was guilty of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continence, when wearied out and forc't by the Adulterer.<note place="margin">St. Austin.</note> 
                  <hi>Duo fuerunt</hi> (ſaith the holy Father) <hi>at unus commiſit Adulterium.</hi> Two they were, and yet but one of them committed Adultery.</p>
               <p>When Judge <hi>Thorp</hi> was condemned to death in Parliament for Bribery The reaſon of that judgement is given, <hi>Quia</hi> (ſaith the Record) <hi>predictus Willielmus Thorpe ſacramentum domini Regis quod erga populum ſuum hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit cuſtodiendum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Parl. <hi>24.</hi> Ed. <hi>3.</hi> part. <hi>3.</hi> Memb. <hi>2.</hi> in Dorſo. Et Fot. Parl. <hi>25</hi> Ed <hi>3.</hi> Pars <hi>10.</hi> memb. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>malicioſe falſe &amp; rebelliter fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>git &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe the ſaid <hi>William Thorp</hi> had broken the Kings Oath, it doth not ſay his own Oath, but the Kings Oath, that ſolemne and grand obligation, which is the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the whole Kingdome, and the knot of the Diadem, ſo that as the Kings Oath may be broken by others, (his own unſpotted honour and juſtice unviolated) ſo likewiſe may his Royal Faith and gracious promiſes as in our caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 5.</hi> The grand Objection of neceſſity and National Danger ſuppoſing alſo our Fears to be at that time juſt) conſidered at large and Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. That the Subjects property is not violable in this State, but by his own conſent, in caſes of far greater National danger then this was, proved by ſundry Records and otherwiſe, the Rapines of <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> and <hi>3d.</hi> upon the Subjects Moneys in Churches, &amp;c. conſidred and anſwered. What courſes the Law hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the preſervation of the Kingdome, where the danger is inſtant and cannot ſtay for a Parliament.</head>
               <p>I am now at length arrived to the grand Objection of this caſe, the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of which I am neceſſitated (though with reluctancy in my ſelf) to conſider, becauſe if this Objection prove impregnable, the Councel of ſtopping the Exchequer may ſeem to be built upon a good, or at leaſtwiſe an exccuſable foundation, and ſo in all that I have hitherto ſaid, <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſeem to have trifled with and eluded my Reader. And herein (becauſe <hi>I</hi> pretend not to any Arcanums of State) <hi>I</hi> ſhall handle this point by way of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, and ſhall ſuppoſe that the fears and jealouſies which at the time of ſhutting the Exchequer did poſſeſs this State were juſt, and ſuch as might well fall upon conſtant and deliberating mindes. The Objection then will run thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> Ob. <hi>That our Neighbour Princes and States were making vaſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for War, that the Heavens about us were black and Cloudy, and where the ſtorm might fall no man could Divine. That</hi> Neceſſitas eſt Lex temporis, Quae non habet Legem. <hi>That neceſſity and ſelf preſervation ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintend all Lawes. That it is more eligible to lop off one member from the Body Politique, or at leaſt wiſe to let an Arm, or perhaps a finger thereof blood, then that the whole ſhould be endangered, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> The Objection <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs is important and weighty, and will deſerve a ſubſtantial Anſwer. In order thereunto <hi>I</hi> muſt in the firſt place mind my Reader that <hi>I</hi> have (as <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe) by irrafregable Argument proved the property of the Subject in this caſe violated. <hi>I</hi> will then add, that it is a Fundamental Law of this Realm, that the Subjects propriety is not violable, no not in caſes of National Danger, without his own free and voluntary conſent, and that, Firſt by the conſent of his own individual
<pb facs="tcp:51796:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſon, or Secondly by that of his Repreſentatives in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hath delegate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his conſent. To prove this I could produce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Records of Parliament and other Courts, but (for brevities ſake) ſhall content my ſelf with ſome few, doing herein like one that chooſeth 5 or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> full eares of Wheat out of a ſelect ſheaf, who muſt neceſſarily leave behind him as good as he takes.</p>
               <p>The firſt Record therefore that I ſhall inſiſt upon, will be that memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble one of 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. in a Writt of Error upon a judgement given in <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in Treſpaſs by <hi>Heyburne</hi> againſt <hi>Keylow,</hi> for entring his houſe, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Cheſt, and taking away 70 <hi>l.</hi> in money upon a ſpecial verdict, the caſe was this.</p>
               <p>The Scots had entred the Biſhoprick with a formidable Army, making great burnings and ſpoil,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 14. <hi>Fd.</hi> 2. B R. <hi>Rot.</hi> 60.</note> the Commonalty of <hi>Durham</hi> (whereof the Plaintiff was one) apprehenſive of the common danger, conſulted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at length agreed to ſend their agents to compound with the Scots, for money to depart, and were all ſworn (the Plaintiff being one) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſuch compoſition, and alſo what Ordinance ſhould be made in that behalt, thereupon they compounded with the Scots for 1600 Marks, but becauſe this Money was to be paid without the leaſt delay, they all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented that <hi>Keylow</hi> the Defendant and others, ſhould go into every mans houſe, to ſearch for ready Money, to make up the ſaid ſumme, and that it ſhould be repayd by the ſame Commonalty, and thereupon the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant entred the Plaintiffs houſe, and took the ſaid 70 <hi>l,</hi> which was paid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that Fine. The Jury were demanded whether the Plaintiff was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and conſented to the taking of the Money, they ſaid no. Whereupon the Plaintiff had Judgement to recover the 70 <hi>l.</hi> upon this Judgement the Defendant brings his Writt of Error in the Kings Bench, and aſſigns er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in point of Law, and there the Judgement was reverſt, becauſe <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> (whoſe Money it was) had agreed to this Ordinance, and was ſworn to perform it, and <hi>Keylow</hi> had done nothing but by the expreſs conſent of <hi>Heyburn,</hi> and therefore was no Treſpaſſor, and that <hi>Heyburn</hi> had no other remedy for his Money, but againſt the Commonalty of <hi>Durham.</hi> By which it appeareth, that if the owner of the money had not particularly concented, ſuch Ordinance could not have bound him, and yet this was in a caſe of imminent danger, and for publique defence.</p>
               <p>The next is a Record of the Parliament of 20 <hi>Ri.</hi> 2. ſome little time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Seſſion,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>2.</hi> Fi. <hi>2.</hi> pars <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the French had actually invaded this Realm, they had burnt <hi>Portſmouth, Dertmouth, Plymouth, Rye</hi> and <hi>Haſtings,</hi> they had poſſeſt themſelves of the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> beſeiged <hi>Winchelſy,</hi> and at length entring the <hi>Thames</hi> with their victorious Fleet, came up to <hi>Graves end,</hi> and burnt moſt part of that Town, and (which was yet worſe) in the North, the Scots had burnt <hi>Roxborough,</hi> and were ready to over run all the North
<pb facs="tcp:51796:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>England,</hi> the Realme being thus beſet both by Sea and Land with the united puiſſance of two mighty Kingdomes, and like a Candle burning at both ends, the publique Treaſure alſo exhauſt; a great Councel was forthwith call'd of the Prelacy, Baronage, and other great men, and Sages (or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) of the Nation, to conſult about theſe difficulties, they came at length to a final reſolution, the which <hi>Scroop,</hi> then Lord Chancellour, delivered to all the Lords in the enſuing Parliament, which (as the Roll above quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſaith) was thus. That unce the laſt Parliament, the ſaid Councel met, and conſidering the great danger the Kingdome was in, and how money might be raiſed for the Common Defence, which could not wait the delay of a Parliament, and how the Kings Coffers had not ſufficient in them, they all concluded that money could not be had for ſuch defence, without lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a charge upon the Commonalty, and that ſuch charge could not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed without a <hi>Parliament;</hi> and the Lords thereupon ſupplyed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity with their own money, and adviſed a Parliament for farther ſupply, and Repayment of themſelves, which was accordingly done.</p>
               <p>I think no man will pretend that our late danger (to ſay no more) was greater than this; and yet becauſe there was no other courſe in thoſe times thought lawful for the raiſing Treaſure upon the Subjects Goods then by their own aſcent in Parliament, only that courſe was then thought fitteſt to be practiſed, which was ſuch as ought to be obeyed.</p>
               <p>The next Record is the Statute of 31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this King had diſſolved the leſſer,<note place="margin">Old booke of Statutes <hi>31.</hi> He. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and in the year of this Statute the greater Monaſteries; which being a new precedent made a great noiſe, and the event thereof was apprehended with terrour and amazement all over the Chriſtian world, this adminiſtred ſecret ſeeds of diſcontent to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the people, which after broke out into open Rebellions (as our Chronicles declare) in ſeveral parts of the Kingdome; this King (though ſtanding as much upon his praerogative as any of his Predeceſſors) to provide againſt the like ſuddain eruptions of this Torrent, which would not ſtay for Parliaments, procures a Statute to be made, that the King for the time being, with the Advice of his Councel, two Biſhops, two chief Juſtices, and divers others, might by His Proclamation, make Ordinances for puniſhing offences, and impoſing penalties, which ſhould have the force of a Law, but with this proviſo [that thereby no mans life, or property, Lands or Goods ſhould be toucht or impeacht] ſo then though the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power was thus corroborated by this Statute, yet the Parliament took care, that no mans Life or Property ſhould be raviſht from him. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever notwithſtanding the ſaid Reſtriction, this Statute was thought incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and thereupon repealed ſoon after, in 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>This Kingdome never laboured under a juſter fear then in the Year 88. when it was aſſaild by that invincible Armada, or Sea-Gyant (as the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:51796:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Bacon</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">His War with Spain.</note> calls it) and yet every mans Right was then preſerved inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Nay the Queen was ſo tender in that particular, that (as our Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſay) She gave Expreſs Order that not ſo much as an Ear of Corn ſhould be burnt,<note place="margin">Cambden in vita Elizab. <hi>1588.</hi>
                  </note> or other Goods of her Subjects devaſtated, until the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy had actually Landed, and was even upon the very point of poſſeſſing the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf. And therefore where the caſe of 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. of plucking down the Suburbs of a City without the conſent of the owners, in time of War, is Law,<note place="margin">8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.</note> it muſt be underſtood of an actual Invaſion of the Enemy, when the danger is in <hi>potentia proxima,</hi> and the Fire ready to take. And this manifeſtly appears by the Record of 11. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. where the Mayor and Citizens of <hi>Dublin</hi> puld down the Suburbs of that City,<note place="margin">Clauſ <hi>11.</hi> Ed <hi>2.</hi> Memb. <hi>19</hi> Dorſo pro ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jore &amp; civibus Dublin.</note> but it was (ſaith the Record) <hi>Super imminentem hoſtilem irruptionem ſcottorum inimicorum infra Hiberniam, &amp; pro ſalvatione Civitatis praedictae, &amp; ne dictis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micis ad Civitatem praedictam facilior pateret ingreſſus &amp;c.</hi> And yet this Corporation neither would not truſt to this point of Law, but for their better ſecurity procured the King's Pardon, which yet was cautiouſly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough drawn, for it was <hi>Pardonamus eis &amp; euilibet de communitate Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis praedictae id quod ad nos pertinet de proſtratione praedicta, &amp;c.</hi> We Pardon as much as in us lies, &amp;c. as appears by <hi>Pat. de anno</hi> 12. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>Memb.</hi> 30. <hi>intus de pardonacione pro majore &amp; Civibus Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo of the caſe of <hi>Graveſend</hi> Barge.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobe Cokes.</hi> 12. Rep. 63.</note> If the Ferry-man may juſtify to throw my Goods over-board to lighten the Veſſel, it muſt be upon an inſtant Tempeſt, and inevitable peril; but if the Ferry-man ſhall ſay, I ſee a Cloud yonder my Maſters, its like to be a great ſtorm, and thereupon ſhall throw them over, I doubt that is not at all juſtifiable in Law.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now draw nearer our own times,<note place="margin">Cokes <hi>3d</hi> Inſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and preſent you with a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virate of precedents (to ſay nothing of the Petition of Right) in one and the ſelf ſame Parliament (no leſs then that which attain'd the name of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamen um Benedictum</hi>) I mean that of 3. <hi>Caroli primi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt the Judgement of the two Houſes in that Parliament in Dr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> caſe,<note place="margin">Ruſhw Hiſt. Collect. <hi>3.</hi> Carol</note> who was ſentenc'd by them principally for declaring in a Sermon (which he afterwards Printed) that the King in Caſes of immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger to the Kingdome, might without Parliament Levy Money up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Subject. There were other collateral charges againſt him its true, but this was the principal,<note place="margin">Journal of both Houſes.</note> and to this he chiefly applyed his Defence, and would have excuſed this Aſſertion by limiting it only to Caſes of Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Extremity, but that would not ſerve his turn, he himſelf ſubmitting, and the Sentence afterwards affirmed by the Kings Proclamation for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Book.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the Commiſſion for <hi>Loane,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruſhw. Hiſt. Collect <hi>3.</hi> Caroli</note> to carry on the War for the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> in which was ſuggeſted the ſafety and very ſubſiſtance of the King, People, and Religion to be in inſtant danger, that his Majeſtie's
<pb facs="tcp:51796:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Coffers were exhauſted, that the ſupply could not ſtay for a Parliament, that the King upon his Acceſſion to the Crown, found himſelf ingaged in this War, and that by advice in Parliament (which I think may deſerve ſome remark) and only lending a little Money for prevention required, Now I would fain know what ſuggeſtions could have poſſibly been more ſubſtantial or perſuaſive, But becauſe this courſe was compulſary, and without conſent, theſe Commiſſions in the ſame Parliament were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be illegal, and ſo conſented to be by his Majeſty,<note place="margin">Poultons Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes <hi>3.</hi> Car. <hi>1.</hi> cap, <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and ſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a little after in the ſame Parliament in the Petition of Right.</p>
               <p>The third is the Commiſſion of Exciſe iſſued to 33.<note place="margin">Ruſhw. Hiſt. collect. <hi>30.</hi> Car.</note> Lords and others of the Privy Councel in which they are commanded to raiſe Moneys by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions or otherwiſe, as in their judgements they ſhall find to be moſt convenient. The Suggeſtions here, were for the moſt part the ſame with thoſe in the above mentioned Commiſſion of <hi>Loane,</hi> and yet adjudged by both Houſes contrary to Law; and the Lords deſired his Majeſty that this Commiſſion of Exciſe might be canceld, and ſhortly after it was canceld by the King, and thereupon brought ſo canceld into the Lords Houſe by the Lord Keeper, and by the Lords ſo ſent to the Commons.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place I ſhall cite the Statute of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. For the Reverſal of the Judgement in the caſe of the Ship-writs, I am not willing (as well of brevity as other reaſons) to recite this Statute at large, but I dare engage that no man ſhall read that Law, but will ſay it is a moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Judgement in the point againſt the violation of propriety in caſe of National danger. If any man however, ſhall for reaſons beſt known to himſelf, Arraign or Calumniate this Act of Parliament, I ſhall ſay no more then this. If it be Law, why may I not vouch it? If it be not, why is it not Repeald? why doth it ſtill cumber our Statute Books?</p>
               <p>I am heartily ſorry to have had ſo invincible an occaſion adminiſtred to me here, of diſturbing the Reſt of theſe ſleeping Muniments of propriety; but this preſumption alſo muſt be added to the black train of thoſe Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which follow this pernicious Councel. It is but natural to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to bring in what Arguments they can to preſerve their undoubted Rights,<note place="margin">Juvenal Saty. 3. <hi>verſus</hi> 152.</note> eſpecially when irritated by that unhappy Thing which renders men not only miſerable, but (as the Poet ſaith) <hi>Ridicule</hi> and <hi>contemn'd.</hi> Neither have I here (I hope) invaded the juſt Regalities of his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſty (for which no perſon hath an higher veneration then my ſelf) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirm'd them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Reſuſuta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. fol. <hi>65.</hi>
                  </note> For (as Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> then Atturney General ſaid) whilſt the Praerogative runs within its ancient and proper Banks, the main Channel thereof is ſo much the ſtronger, for Overflowes (he adds) evermore hurt the River.<note place="margin">Guilme Jermyes Commentary on the Cuſtomier of <hi>Normandy.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If any man after all this Evidence be yet unſatisfyed in this point, I will ſend him to <hi>France</hi> (for I would rather find a Preſident there) and adviſe
<pb facs="tcp:51796:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>him to conſider the caſe of <hi>Normandy.</hi> That Dutchy had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome time rak'd with Exactions contrary to their Franchiſe and Cuſtomes, and thereupon complain to <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> the then French King, he by his Charter in the year 1314. recognizing the Right &amp; Priveledges of theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the injuſtice of their Grievances, grants that from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they ſhall be diſcharged from all Subſidies and Impoſitions to be laid upon them by him or his Succeſſors, yet with this deadly ſting in the tail of all <hi>[Si neceſſitie grand ne le requiret, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs in caſes of great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity]</hi> which Minute and almoſt inſenſible exception we ſee hath eaten up (upon the matter) all their immunities,<note place="margin">Comines Hiſt. of <hi>France,</hi> Lib. <hi>13. Forteſcue</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> for though theſe States do annually aſſemble, yet their Conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion is little better then the carkaſs of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they are become but the neceſſary Executioners of the Royal pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ay, but did not our</hi> Ed. 1. and Edw. 3. <hi>do greater things then ſtopping the Exchequer? are not our Chronicles full, of their breaking even into the Churches and Abbies, and raviſhing the Treaſure of the Subject for Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of their Warrs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Admitting this Allegation to be true, I Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, we diſcourſe not here what hath been done, <hi>de facto,</hi> but what may be done <hi>de Jure.</hi> And to counterballance theſe, we may put other Princes of this Realm of a contrary complexion into the other Scale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor reſtored the <hi>Danegeld</hi> Money (a grievous Taxe formerly in uſe here) to the perſons from whom it was exacted,<note place="margin">Polydore Virgil. Riba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ra Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave Surius.</note> it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him (as no mean Authors write) that he ſaw the Devil danceing and triumphing upon that vaſt heap of Treaſure, when he was conducted by his Officers to view the ſame. And (by the way) this Act of ſingular piety he did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lden's</hi> Mare clauſum, Lib <hi>2</hi> Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Gloſſary title Danegueld</note> when his people laboured under a dreadful Famine.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second (ſay our Chronicles) maintain'd great Wars, and obtaind a larger Dominion then pertain'd at any other time to this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and notwithſtanding never demanded Subſidy of his Subjects;<note place="margin">Speed, Baker, Haywards Hen <hi>4.1.</hi> part p. <hi>56</hi>
                  </note> and yet his Treaſure after his death was found to be, Nine hundred thouſand pounds beſide, his Jewels and Plate. Certainly a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious ſumme in thoſe dayes!</p>
               <p>It is notorious alſo that <hi>Queen Mary</hi> did by her Letters Patents, of her meer Grace and great Clemency for the ſuccour and relief of her loving Subjects (ſaith that Record) pardon and remit a whole Subſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> given by them to her Predeceſſor,<note place="margin">Old Statutes <hi>1</hi> Maria ſeſſio <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> which releaſe was afterward confirm'd by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> alſo remitted one Subſidy of four granted to her ſaying,<note place="margin">Cambden vita Elizabeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>It w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> all one toher, whether the Money were in Her Subjects Coffers or her own</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly theſe Depredations begot many good Lawes for the firmer
<pb facs="tcp:51796:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>munition of property for future time, and particularly this violence of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. was executed in the <hi>25th.</hi> year of his Reign, and in that very year (and not in 340 as our Printed Statute Books ſay) was made the Statute <hi>de Tallagio non concedendo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Repub. lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> with which the Engliſh defend themſelves (faith <hi>Bodine</hi>) <hi>quaſi Clypeo,</hi> as with a Buckler againſt their Prince.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this King (as our Chronicles affirm) layd this outrage much to heart, and that before his Royal Pallace at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> invironed with infinite numbers of his people, thither by him purpoſely ſummoned, and being rais'd upon an Aſcent or Pedeſtal, the better to be heard and ſeen,<note place="margin">Lib. 3. cap. 9. columna 2510.</note> the Prince, Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> alſo ſtanding with him. <hi>Rogavit populum accepta licentia</hi> (ſaith Knighton) <hi>ut omnia condonaretur ei, &amp; orarent pro eo.</hi> He earneſtly intreated the people that they would forgive him, and pray for him. And <hi>Matthew Weſtminſter</hi> goes yet farther <hi>Kex erumpentibus lacrymis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>veniam de com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis humillime poſtulavit.</hi> The King burſting forth into Tears,<note place="margin">Math. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter. pag. 409. 410.</note> did moſt humbly aske pardon for what he had done (a paſſionate tranſport of a Prince that before that time had rendred himſelf redout table among the <hi>Saracens</hi> as well as the <hi>French,</hi> and that had triumpht over <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Wales!</hi>) And after he had excuſed himſelf to them, with all the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Expreſſion adds. <hi>Et omnia oblata reddam vobis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. Weſtm. ibid.</note> And I will reſtore all that I have forct from you And in purſuance of this promiſe forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with makes an<note n="*" place="margin">Bundelae Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium de priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sigillo in Turre <hi>London.</hi> Anno 25. Ed. 1. &amp; pat. 26 Ed. 1. Mem. 21.</note> Ordination of Councel (which have ſeen in French, and can produce the Copy) to iſſue forth Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> into all the Counties of <hi>England,</hi> to enquire what things had been forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly taken by his Officers, out of the Churches or elſe where, from the Clergy or Laytye, either to guard the Seas, or for any other purpoſe, with Warrants or without, during his Wars with <hi>France,</hi> and to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe matters. <hi>Et et qu ſerra pris, ſeit returne a ceaux, qe le damage ont receu</hi> (ſaith the Record) And that thoſe things that were forct away might be return'd to them that had receiv'd the damage, and to puniſh the parties offending, which<note n="*" place="margin">Pat. 26. Ed. 1. Memb. 21. inquirendo ſuper grava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus popu lo Regnifacti &amp;c.</note> Commiſſions were accordingly executed (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of which I have ſeen, and can produce the Copies) in which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many excellent particulars, too long here to be recited. And for thoſe ſmall Remainders of Moneys which hapned not to be reſtored or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied by vertue of thoſe Commiſſions, they were two or three years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter recovered in the very ordinary Courts of Juſtice, to prove which (among many others) <hi>I</hi> will eite this one Record. <hi>Coia. Pa.</hi> 29. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>Rot.</hi> 18. <hi>The King</hi> pro urgentiſſimis Regni negotiis, &amp; pro defentione totius Regni <hi>(ſaith the Record) had ſeized divers ſummes of money in all the Abbies, Cathedrals, and Religious Houſes within the Realm,</hi> &amp; (quo citius commode poterit) <hi>promiſed repayment: In the Parliament of</hi> 29 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>at</hi> Lincoln <hi>the King is Petitioned for repayment, who promiſeth payment.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:51796:15"/>Ita quod Regis conſcientia ſuper hoc exoneretur, <hi>and there, and</hi> Rot. 19. <hi>Divers ſummes are adjudged to be repaid.</hi> Again it is not at all probable this Prince would be negligent in paying his own, that was ſo juſt in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying his Fathers Debts (as we find by our Records) ſo that upon the whole matter,<note place="margin">Pot. <hi>4.</hi> Ed. <hi>1.</hi> Memb. <hi>19.</hi> intut</note> notwithſtanding this Objection; <hi>I</hi> think we may concurr well enough with Sir <hi>William Herle</hi> Ch. Juſtice of the <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> who in 5. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. ſaith of this <hi>Ed.</hi> 1,<note place="margin">Paſch. 5. Ed 3 caſus 5.</note> (in whoſe time he lived) <hi>Que fuit pluis ſage Roy que unques fuit.</hi> That he was one of the wiſeſt Kings that ever was in the World.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. his Rapines likewiſe produc't very benificial Lawes to the Subject, as will be manifeſt to any man that ſhall peruſe the Statutes of that time.<note place="margin">Fot. Alminiae <hi>12.</hi> Ed. <hi>3</hi> Mem. <hi>22</hi> in Dorſo De excuſando R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge populam verſut.</note> They were actions which he never juſtified, but excuſed alway with ſingular Reſentments. As appears by his Letter (extant upon Record) to <hi>John Stratford</hi> then Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the Tallages and Exactions with which he had burdened his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which (be faith) he could not mention without inexpreſſible grief of mind, and there excuſeth himſelf upon the inevitable neceſſity of his warrs, and deſires the Arch-biſhop to ſatisfy the people, and to ſtir them up to pray for him, hoping ere long he ſhould make them compenſation, and give them comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>There remains yet one Objection with which I am infore't to encounter,</hi> ſe defendendo, <hi>becauſe I perceive it ready to aſſail me. And that is, that the Parliament is a great Body, (I ſpeak it with all due reverence) and moves ſlowly, and therefore if the Law allow not ſome other courſe (as this of ſtopping the Exchequer or the like) in raiſing money in caſe of ſuddain Danger, the Kingdome may be loſt before the Parliament can ſupply.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> To this I anſwer, That all Warrs are either Offenſive or Defenſive. If it be Offenſive, it cannot be ſuddain, for it is the King's own Act, and the reſult of mature deliberation; and ſo their may be time enough to call a Parliament, if it ſtand with his Sacred Majeſtie's good will and pleaſure. If it be a Defenſive War by Forreign invaſion, which <hi>I</hi> ſhall (to avoid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil) agree may be ſuddain (though a great Stateſman tells us,<note place="margin">Comines fol. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note> that theſe Clouds are commonly viſible afar off before the Tempeſt fall) <hi>I</hi> ſay if by Forreign Invaſion, then firſt the impulſe of ſelf-preſervation (an indelible Character wrote on every man's mind by the very band of Nature) will diſpoſe all Mankind to expoſe their Lives and Eſtates, which otherwiſe they muſt inevitably loſe. And this ſeems to be the caſe of this Kingdome in the Year 88.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ambden vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Eliza.</note> for there was then no Parliament ſitting, but many of the Worthies of that time, (ſome of whoſe names are tranſmitted to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) at their own private charges, brought in men and Ships to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Defence.</p>
               <p>But Secondly, if we are to ſuppoſe that men muſt be drag'd and haled to their own preſervation; I ſay then the Law hath provided, that in caſe
<pb facs="tcp:51796:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Forreign invaſion, every Subject within the Land, high or low, whether he hold of the King or not, may be compel'd at his own charge, to ſerve the King in perſon. To prove this I can vouch Authorities from Common Law. Statutes and Records which for brevity <hi>I</hi> will not quote at large, but (leaſt any man ſhould doubt hereof) will only point where they may be found.</p>
               <p>Common Law, ſee 7. H. 4. <hi>Brook Tenures</hi> 44. &amp; 73. <hi>Fitch.</hi> Protection 100. <hi>Coke</hi> 7. <hi>Re.</hi> 7. <hi>b. Calvins caſe.</hi> 2 <hi>Rolls Title Impoſition</hi> 165. &amp;c. 1 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 69. <hi>b. in fine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Statute Laws ſee (among many others) 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Records (among many others that <hi>I</hi> have ſeen) <hi>I</hi> will crave leave to vouch two.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is 14. <hi>Johannis Regis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. Paris <hi>223.</hi> Matth. Weſtm. <hi>92.</hi>
                  </note> where upon an imminent French in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, <hi>King John</hi> iſſues our Writts, in which he ſummons all his Subjects, high and low to repair forthwith to <hi>Dover. Ad defendendum caput no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum</hi> (ſaith the Record) <hi>&amp; capita ſuae, &amp; quod nullue remaneat qui Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma portare poſſit ſub nomine</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Baſe Cowardiſe or Turwail ſo the gloſſaries</note> 
                  <hi>Culvertagij, &amp; perpetuae ſervitutis &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other is upon a French invaſion too, deſign'd againſt this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in 26. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the which being a Record ſo appoſite to my purpoſe <hi>I</hi> ſhall recite ſomewhat more at large.<note place="margin">Rot. Franciae Anno <hi>26.</hi> Ed. <hi>3.</hi> Memb. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex dilecto conſanguineo &amp; fideli ſuo Henrico Duci Lancaſtriae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Quia Adverſarij noſtri Franciae nos &amp; Regnum noſtrum Angliae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadere machinantes, ad nos &amp; Dominium noſtrum, &amp; totam nationem Anglicanam pro viribus deſtruend. Nos conſiderantes omnes Incolas dicti Regni cujuſcunque conditionis extiterint, cum verſetur commune pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum teneri de jure pro patriâ pugnare, &amp; eam contrae hoſtiles aggreſſus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſare. —vobis mandamus quod omnes homines defenſabiles tam milites &amp; Armigeros quam alios quoſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de dicto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ducatu cujuſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſtatus ſeu conditionis fuerint arraiari, &amp; quemlibet eorum iuxta ſtatum &amp; faculates ſuas, Equitaturis &amp; Armit competentib us muniri &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhall conclude this Section with a caſe of very recent Memory, and of ſingular Notoriety throughout the whole Kingdome, I mean that of the Conflagration of our Ships by the <hi>Dutch</hi> not many years paſt in the River of <hi>Chatham.</hi> There prevail'd at that time an univerſal jealoufy among the people that upon this occaſion ſome ſuddain ſtop might be put upon the Exchequer, and thereupon the Bankers were exerciſed with reſtleſs ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations for the ſpeedy payment of their Debts. The King for the ſedati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Fears and apprehenſions,<note place="margin">See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration at the end of this Treatiſe.</note> is adviſed (and not without infinite prudence) to iſſue forthwith his Declaration to preſerve inviolable the courſe of payments in the Exchequer, which was accordingly done. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee what were the grounds of this Declaration. Why truly they are expreſt there to be. Firſt, <hi>Leaſt the Credit of the Bankers (who had been ſo uſeful to the King) might be weakned.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Leaſt the King's Securities might be undervalued.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Leaſt in conſequence the publick
<pb facs="tcp:51796:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Safety might be endangered.</hi> Now all that <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſay is this. That (of what valew in reaſon of State it may be, <hi>I</hi> know not, but) to men of vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Negotiation it ſeems a Riddle and matter inextricable, that theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations which at that time appeard to have been of ſo politique and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Regard, within the ſpace of two or three years, upon a like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſhould be thought by this Adviſor clearly Obſolete, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther void of Prudence; And the Credits of the Exchequer, Royal ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the publique ſafety ſo little by him conſulted. <hi>Idem manens idem, ſemper facit idem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have at length diſcharg'd my ſelf of this grand and Coloſſus Objection, in how tolerable meaſure I muſt leave to the Candor of my intelligent Reader; But if it happen that I have herein given a ſubſtantial and effective anſwer thereunto, I dare ſay this pernicious Councel hath then no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſupport, but muſt of neceſſity fall to the ground.</p>
               <p>However I am to enter my Proteſtation, that I would gladly have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd ſo ſublime and important an Argument, if the nature of this diſcourſe had not (much againſt my own inclination) compeld me to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">That this Councel is contrary to the Policies that have been practiſed heretofore by the wiſeſt Forreign States of the World, in far greater Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igencies then ours. The Objection (of Princes not repaying money lent them by their Subjects to keep them in better Obedience) Anſwered. The inconvenience that hapned at <hi>Rome</hi> upon an Impeachement of the <hi>Bankers</hi> and <hi>Uſurers.</hi> That perſons concerned here in the Stop of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> will be loſers by loſs of opportunities for bargains, &amp;c. in this interval.</head>
               <p>ALL men agree that <hi>Rome</hi> (whether Monarchical or Republique) was a State founded upon the choiceſt Polities that ever were practiſed in the world.<note place="margin">In proemio ad Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> And (as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith) he that reads their Atcheivements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates not the Geſts and Actions of one ſingle people, but even of all mankind. Let us then conſider, what expedients this ſo prudent a Nation exerciſed in caſes of like nature.</p>
               <p>It is plain this State was never under a ſtreighter dureſs or pinch then after their diſmal defeat at the Battail of <hi>Cannae,</hi> for then had <hi>Hanibal</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:51796:16"/>broke into <hi>Italy</hi> like a Deluge of the Sea, bearing down all before him, and at length this Tempeſt of War had begirt the very walls even of <hi>Rome,</hi> with his triumphant Army, and which was yet worſe, the Roman Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury was totally exhauſt.</p>
               <p>In this Extremity <hi>Levinus</hi> and <hi>Marcellus</hi> the Conſulls declare forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by Edict, That each private perſon of ſuch an Eſtate (and ſo others proportionably) ſhould furniſh out a Souldier at their own charge for thirty dayes. <hi>Ad id-edictum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Livy</hi>) <hi>Tantus fremitus hominum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Livii. Lib. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>tanta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> indignatio fuit, ut magis Dux quam materia ſeditionis, deeſſet.</hi> Upon this Edict ſo hot was the rage and petulancy of the people, that there wanted nothing but a Leader, to have put all into a cumbuſtion: The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty crying out that they had now for many years been loaded with Tributes that their Lands lay freſh and devaſtated, and that they could not by any force be compel'd to give that, which they had not to give: And this and much more they ſpake, not in corners, but even in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place, and in the hearing of the very Conſuls themſelves. In ſo great an Agony of the Body Politique, the Lords of the Senate Aſſembled, to conſult how they might with more ſecurity Levy Money, and ſtring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a freſh with new Sinews of War; after many temerarious courſes propoſed and rejected,<note place="margin">Livii lib. <hi>26.</hi> Flori lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> they thus reaſoned (as <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Florus</hi> relate) amongſt themſelves. <hi>Omne aurum</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Argentum Aes ſignatum ad Triumviros Menſarios deferamus, nullo ante ſenatûs conſulto facto, ut vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria oblatio, &amp;c.</hi> Let us our ſelves that be Senators firſt bring into the publique Treaſury all our Gold Silver and Money, and this too with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any formal Decree, that ſo this voluntary Oblation of ours may excite an emulation of ſupplying the Common-wealth, firſt in thoſe of the <hi>Equeſtrian</hi> Order, and then of the Commonalty; In purſuance of this propoſal, the Lords of the Senate brought in all their Treaſure according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Now ſee what the conſequence hereof was.<note place="margin">Livii lib. <hi>26.</hi> Flori. Lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Hereupon (ſay the ſame Hiſtorians) the Knights and Gentlemen followed the example of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, and the Commoners that of the Knights and Gentlemen; And the Contributions were ſo large, and the Conflicts ſo ſharpe for priority of regiſtring names, that the Exchequer had hardly Books and Clarkes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to enter the particulars.<note place="margin">Bodin de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>2d</hi> Aerario.</note> 
                  <hi>Bodine</hi> commenting upon this proſperous Councel, hath theſe very words. <hi>Cum Annibal Italiam quateret, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemque ipſam obſideret, Senatus diruto aerario nova tributa ſubditis aut ſociis imperari noluir. Nihilenim prementibus hoſtibus tam periculoſum.</hi> When <hi>Hannibal</hi> had made <hi>Italy</hi> to tremble, and had beſieged <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, the Senate, though the publique Treaſure were ſpent, would not impoſe new Tributes upon their Subjects and Colleagues; For nothing (ſaith he) can be more hazardous upon an inſtant impreſſion of an Enemy. Neither is it to be forgotten, that the ſame Hiſtorians add, that <hi>parta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> victoria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:51796:17"/>That after Victory obtain'd,<note place="margin">Livii Lib. <hi>26.</hi> &amp; Lib. <hi>31.</hi> Boden Lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> diſcomfited, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate had decreed the Repayment of every Lenders Money juſtly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably, which was Executed accordingly.</p>
               <p>The Learned <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erus</hi> Relates a Story very appoſite to this purpoſe. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus Dux</hi> Neopolitanus <hi>victus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fugatuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab hoſte,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Boterus de politia Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium &amp;c. Lib. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> Duke of <hi>Naples</hi> being vanquiſht of the Enemy, flies to <hi>Naples,</hi> and there conſults about raiſing Money for the reinforcing of his Army, and had reſolved (by the Advice of perſons more factious then wiſe, faith that Author) to effect this by impoſition of new and unuſuall Taxes, this being intimated to one <hi>Gorellus</hi> (a perſon of ſingular Prudence and Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) he forthwith repairs to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, and beſpeaks him after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>I am afraid</hi> (GREAT SIR) <hi>that whilſt you are ſolicitous of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the Enemy, you take no care of falling into the hatred and Malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of your own Subjects, by this impoſition of a new Tribute:</hi> I <hi>beſeech you Sir, what can your greatest Enemies breath after with a warmer zeal then that you ſhould follow a Councel, that will aſſuredly diſpotle you of the Love and fidelity of your people. Baniſh then</hi> GREAT SIR, <hi>out of your Royal Breaſt ſo pernicious a determination; for that money which you want, my ſelf with ſome other of your ſervants (who are to run the ſame Riſques of Fortune with your Majeſty) will preſently ſupply you;</hi> And taking a Pen in his hand, he put down what each perſon (himſelf princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally) was to pay, and the Money was in a moment brought in, <hi>Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum ſane prore &amp; tempore, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Boterus.</hi> A moſt prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel for the matter and occaſion, given by <hi>Gorellus,</hi> and approved by the Duke, by which (ſaith he) the wiles of the Enemy were prevented, and the popular quiet and contentment conſulted.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe contraries appear beſt by oppoſition, I will produce one inſtance a little diverſe from this. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> had ſuddain news brought him of a vaſt Army in the raiſing by <hi>Mark Antony</hi> to encounter with him; The Prize to be ſought for was no leſs then the Empire of the World. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> (being young, and inſtigated by evil Councel) ſquee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the people with Taxes towards the ſurport of this War. The people hereupon began to Mutiny,<note place="margin">Invita An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonii.</note> inſomuch that (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> Reports) the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt men of that time took it for granted, that if <hi>Antony</hi> in this conjuncture had approacht nearer with his Army, the Romans would have aſſuredly revolted, and delivered up <hi>Caeſar</hi> into the hands of his Enemy. But (as he ſaith) the imprudent delaies of <hi>Antony</hi> gave time to the people of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocting their diſcontents, and of the ſedation of their Paſſions; neither is it to be neglected that this Illuſtrious perſon, after the defeat of <hi>Antony,</hi> and his own acceſs to the Empire, took ſuch warning by this hazzardous miſtake, that ever after he abandoned all Councels of this Nature. And unto that degree that in the laſt twenty years of his Reign, he laid out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:51796:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Publique Benefits and Emoluments of the Common-wealth (as <hi>Seutonius</hi> writes) little leſs then <hi>Quater decies Millies</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See for this valuation</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daens de Aſſe. Hackwel's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology <hi>and</hi> Savil's <hi>notes on</hi> Tacitus Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeſtcrtium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">vita Octavii cap. Ultimo.</note> That is, <hi>Eleven Millions, Eighty thouſand five hundred thirty three pounds ſix ſhillings eight pence Sterling: Befides his two paternal patrimonies, and other his Inheritances. Others report, thirty five Millions of Gold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the two aforeſaid patrimonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. Many other examples of like naturel could produce out of Hiſtory and Policy, which yet (for brevity ſake) I forbear to do, and haſten to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer an objection, <hi>viz.</hi> That (as <hi>certain Authors</hi> affirm) ſome <hi>Princes</hi> have by great <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuries Decoyed</hi> vaſt ſummes of their Subjects Moneys into their <hi>Exchequers,</hi> and forborn afterwards to repay them,<note place="margin">Life of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> bound up with <hi>Plutarche</hi> Lives.</note> on purpoſe to oblige their people to a <hi>ſtricter Obedience</hi> and <hi>fidelity to the Crown,</hi> And this <hi>Artifice</hi> (as <hi>Bodine</hi> Reports) was recommended as a ſubtle project to the French Kings, and accordingly practiſed by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> I ſhall anſwer this <hi>Objection</hi> in the very words of the ſame <hi>Bodine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De repub. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> in an other place. <hi>Hee quidem tolerabilia viderentur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Si quod Regibus noſtris perſuaſum erat, Civitates, obſequie &amp; fide majore, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis mutuo pecuniis, devincire potuiſſent, ſed nullis temporibus graviores in Gallia tumultus, aut plures Civitatum defectiones, extiterunt.</hi> Theſe Councels had been tollerable <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> if as theſe State-Mountebanks would perſwade our Kings, the people by this deteiner of their Money would have been conteind in better Obedience, but alaſs, there were never more dangerous Tumults in <hi>France,</hi> or more frequent Revolts of Cities known, then in thoſe very times.<note place="margin">Eſſayes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>All <hi>States</hi> have tollerated <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuries</hi> in one kind or Rate or other, <hi>And it is impoſſible</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>) <hi>to conceive the inconveniencies that will enſue not only to Merchants but all other perſons if the borrowing of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys ſhould be cramp'd and diſcouraged:</hi> Therefore conſideration for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys lent bath been entertaind (as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith) of the <hi>Judaical Divorces</hi>) for the <hi>Hardneſs of mens hearts.</hi> And the <hi>Endeavours</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing thereof have proved ſometimes <hi>inconvenient and dangerous to the States</hi> where it hath been attempted;<note place="margin">Annalium l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> To prove which I ſhall produce but one Example reported by <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> who tells us, that in the Reign of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar. Magna vis accuſatorum in eos irrupit qui pecunias ſaenore auctitabant, &amp;c.</hi> That a great Rabble of Informers roſe up againſt thoſe perſons which took exceſſive <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> and thereupon every man cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his Debts, on a ſuddain enſued a great want and ſcarcity of money, and an univerſal diſcontent, and the aſpect of affairs ſeem d not very pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitious, which being perceived by that prudent Empero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, he forthwith caus'd an hundred Million of<note n="*" place="margin">l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> s d. <hi>791466 13.4.</hi> ſterling.</note> 
                  <hi>Seſterces</hi> of his own to be put into the <hi>Bank</hi> to be lent to all men that had occaſion for three years without intereſt, and thereupon all things-became calm and ſedate again.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Lastly, though the <hi>Exchoquer</hi> here be again opened (as in good time I hope it will) yet the perſons therein concern'd will notwithſtanding ſuſtain <hi>infinite damage,</hi> in point of irreparable loſs of thoſe opportunityes of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious <hi>Bargains, Marriages,</hi> and <hi>ſundry other particulars, which in this interval</hi> ſave been offered unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <head type="sub">That this Councel is contrary to the Common Reaſon of Mankind, and in ſome reſpects againſt the Rules of humanity. That it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the credit of his Majeſties <hi>Exchequer.</hi> The caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Phillip</hi> the Second of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Banker</hi> of <hi>Genoa,</hi> truly ſtated, and demonſtrated to be eſſentially different from our caſe. <hi>Campanella's</hi> Advice to King <hi>Phillip</hi> to make ſpeedy payment of that Debt.</head>
               <p>IT is a <hi>Rule</hi> that hath prevail'd among all Nations (as well <hi>Barbarous</hi> as <hi>Civil</hi>) That <hi>Quod Omnes tangit ab omnibus debet ſupportari.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Qui ſentit commodum, ſentire debet &amp; onus.</hi> Where the utility and peril is common, there the charge and contribution ought to be common alſo. But I doubt if this <hi>Councel</hi> happen to be weighed in this <hi>Ballance</hi> it will prove light, for as it is plain that the <hi>Defence</hi> of the Kingdome was an <hi>utility</hi> to the whole, ſo it is as evident that the <hi>charge</hi> thereof was faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon a <hi>Part.</hi> What is this but as if the <hi>States of Holland</hi> ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the expenſe of <hi>defending</hi> their <hi>Countrey</hi> from the <hi>Sea,</hi> upon a <hi>parcel</hi> of their <hi>people?</hi> Or (if we may compare great things with ſmall) as if the <hi>Banks</hi> and <hi>Walls</hi> of the great <hi>Level of the Fenns,</hi> ſhould be maintained by a <hi>ſmall</hi> number of the <hi>Proprietors?</hi> And yet this ſeems to be the preſent caſe, and how far this proceeding is contrary to the common Reaſon of Mankind. I leave to the world to judge.</p>
               <p>But this is not all neither, For this charge is not laid only upon a <hi>Part,</hi> but in great meaſure upon the <hi>moſt impotent</hi> and <hi>neceſſitous</hi> part of the Kingdome, and upon many of thoſe <hi>glorious Worthies</hi> which maugre all the <hi>Temptations and menaces of wicked men preſerved their Virgin Loyalty chaſt and undeſlowred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have obſerved that ſome perſons in <hi>Parliaments</hi> have uſed it as a <hi>motive</hi> to <hi>ſupply</hi> our <hi>Kings</hi> with <hi>Money,</hi> becauſe ſay they, that which you give,
<pb facs="tcp:51796:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>is but like a <hi>vapour exhaled by the Sun,</hi> which gathereth into a <hi>cloud,</hi> and in ſhort time <hi>diſtils</hi> again upon the Earth in <hi>gentle</hi> dews, and <hi>fructify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſhowres. But this <hi>Advice,</hi> what was it but to draw up the <hi>Tears</hi> of <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>Widdowes,</hi> the <hi>milk</hi> of <hi>helpleſs Babes, the ſweat of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers brow, and the heart blood of ſeveral poor</hi> Loyalliſts, <hi>(among others) to fertilitate the Lands of many perſons which (not to ſay worſe) wallow in all Afluence and Riches?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 3.12. <hi>compar'd with</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.2.</note> Or (if I may uſe a <hi>Scripture Metaphor</hi>) to take <hi>two Leggs,</hi> or a piece of an <hi>Ear</hi> of a <hi>Lambe,</hi> which we had <hi>reſcued</hi> out of <hi>the Jaws</hi> of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cromwel</hi> Sequeſtrators, Committee mens decimators, &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>Lyon, and give it to the</hi> Rich men that have many <hi>Flocks</hi> &amp;. <hi>Herds.</hi> For nothing is more <hi>evident,</hi> then that many of thoſe <hi>wretched perſon; that had but one hundred pound in all the world, had that</hi> All <hi>taken from them towards the</hi> Defence <hi>of the</hi> Kingdome, when many others that were worth <hi>hundred thouſands, expended not a farthing</hi> at that time. And now what I ſhall ſay more—<hi>Pudet haec opprobia nobis</hi>
                  <q>Et dici potuiſſe &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the <hi>Influences</hi> this <hi>Councel</hi> may have upon his <hi>Majeſties Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer,</hi> in all likelyhood they cannot prove very <hi>propitious</hi> and <hi>benigne.</hi> Few things have been more dear to <hi>Princes</hi> then the <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of their <hi>Exchequers,</hi> And <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> wars ſo punctual in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that in her time (they ſay) it went for a Proverb. <hi>As ſure as Checke.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lord Herberts H. 8.</note> For (as a great Authour Writes) <hi>Outward eſteem and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the ſame to great perſons and Things, which the Skin is to the Fruit, which though it is but a ſlight and delicate cover, yet without it the Fruit will be ſubject to diſcolour and Rot.</hi> He that hath a mind to contemplate the <hi>Conſequences</hi> of a <hi>diſcredited Treaſury</hi> let him but conſider the Caſes of <hi>Henry the ſecond of France,</hi> Reported by <hi>Bodine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bodine <hi>Lib 2. cap 4 in fine,</hi> Lord Herberts Hen <hi>8.</hi> laſt leaf but one.</note> and of our King <hi>Henry the 8th.</hi> by the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> (for I would rather they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them then <hi>I</hi>) And I am afraid that when men ſhall be importun'd to lend money upon any <hi>future Occaſion,</hi> they will be apt enough to diſcourſe within themſelves, <hi>That that which hath been done may be done again,</hi> and that the <hi>Moneys</hi> of other men were ſecured unto them by <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Acts of Parliaments,</hi> and that they cannot expect higher <hi>ſecurities</hi> then theſe, &amp;c. It is true indeed when the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is again opened, this <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> will be in good meaſure anſwered, but till that time I fear it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main not inconſiderable.</p>
               <p>I ſhall no farther pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſue the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> of this <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uncel</hi> in this particular (it being ſo obvious to the meaneſt underſtanding) but ſhall now <hi>ſtate</hi> the <hi>Caſe</hi> between <hi>Phillip</hi> the Second of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Bankers</hi> of <hi>Genoa,</hi> as I have extracted it out of the beſt <hi>Authors</hi> I could find, which treat upon that Subject.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles the Fifth Emperour of</hi> Germany, had for a long ſeaſon revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:51796:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>in his mind how he might render the <hi>State of Genoa</hi> obſequious and dependant upon himſelf,<note place="margin">Thuani Firſt lib. <hi>61.</hi> anno Dom. <hi>1575.</hi> Metarani Hiſt. Belgica Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Bodine de repu Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella Spaneſh Monarchy c. <hi>21. Helyns Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mography in</hi> Genoa. Laſſels. Voyage into <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, 1</hi> part. pa. <hi>99.</hi> cum multis alus.</note> and this he did (among other reaſons) that he might as occation ſerved with the greater fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ility Tranſport his Armyes out of <hi>Spain</hi> thorough this Territory into <hi>Italy.</hi> In order to this, ſundry <hi>Experiments</hi> had he made, which yet by the <hi>jealouſies</hi> of that <hi>people</hi> were alwayes readred <hi>improſperous. Charles</hi> (being as he was a Prince of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious <hi>Subtility</hi>) falls upon new <hi>Councels,</hi> he conſidered he had to do with a <hi>people</hi> that dealt much in <hi>Money,</hi> and were generally great <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and <hi>Merchants,</hi> and therefore concluded that if by extraordinary <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuries</hi> he could allure their <hi>Money</hi> into his <hi>Exchequer,</hi> he ſhould then be in poſſeſſion of the beſt <hi>Hoſtages</hi> they could give him for their <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Obſervance.</hi> This <hi>Emperour</hi> dying, <hi>Phillip</hi> his Son, after his <hi>Fathers</hi> Example (to make theſe birds more confident, and leſs jealous of the Snare) proceeds for ſome time to feed theſe unhappy <hi>money-changers</hi> with exceſſive <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> till by this fine <hi>Dexterity</hi> he had conveyed into his bands no leſs then 420. <hi>Datch Tun of Gold,</hi> ſome ſay <hi>eleven,</hi> others <hi>eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen millions of Gold,</hi> and then ſecures this <hi>Debt</hi> to them very fairly upon the <hi>Tribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Indies.</hi> The filly <hi>Birds</hi> were now very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and Sate fair, and there wanted nothing but the <hi>drawing</hi> the Net. Thereupon King <hi>Phillip</hi> (being exhauſted with his <hi>Low-Country Wars</hi> and with all) ſenſible of the <hi>weight</hi> of ſo ponderous a <hi>Debt,</hi> takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at firſt to cavil at ſome little <hi>miſreckonings</hi> in the <hi>Accounts,</hi> and a while after inſiſted that he had hereto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e paid them more <hi>Intereſt money</hi> then they ought to have received, and therefore (quoth he) that <hi>overplus</hi> ought in all reaſon to be deducted out of the <hi>Principal,</hi> and thereupon by <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> Edict (taking the <hi>Opportunity</hi> likewiſe of ſome <hi>Civil diſcords,</hi> which at that time <hi>raged</hi> among them) forthwith ſtops their <hi>Penſions</hi> iſſuable out of the ſaid <hi>Tributes.</hi> And then to <hi>forti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> this <hi>Act,</hi> by ſecret <hi>Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with the <hi>Pope</hi> (to render the Action more ſpecious) procures a <hi>Bull</hi> from his <hi>Holineſs</hi> to confirm all that he had done, however for ſo much <hi>Principal</hi> Money as was afterward agreed to be due (which in the year 1600. I find was One <hi>Million</hi> and half of <hi>Gold</hi>) the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> hath ever ſince to this day juſtly and Honurably ſatisfied the Intereſt.</p>
               <p>This is the true <hi>ſtate of this Caſe</hi> (according to my <hi>diſcovery</hi> thereof). Now it will be evident to any perſon that ſhall <hi>compare</hi> theſe <hi>two caſes</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that they differ each from other in ſundry <hi>eſſential circumſtances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> this <hi>Severity</hi> of King <hi>Phillip</hi> was not <hi>exerted</hi> upon <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> but upon a <hi>Forreign State,</hi> of which <hi>Spain</hi> had then juſt cauſes of <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Jealouſy,</hi> and ſo the Action well enough conſiſtent with the <hi>Rules of Policy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly</hi> the <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Enormity</hi> of this <hi>Feate,</hi> was by a curious <hi>Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demain juggled</hi> upon his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and King <hi>Phillip</hi> to all outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance rendred innocent thereof:<note place="margin">Helin's Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mograph.</note> This Debt (ſaith <hi>Peter Heylin</hi>) was cut off by the <hi>Pope's</hi> Authority, that ſo King <hi>Phillip</hi> might be obliged to that <hi>See. Hoc</hi> debitum (ſaith <hi>Metaranus</hi>) <hi>per pontificis decretum propter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes uſuras fuit diminutum, &amp; moderatum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bodin. de Rep. <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 2</note> This <hi>Debt</hi> by the <hi>Pope's</hi> Decree was moderated upon pretence of exceſſive <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And <hi>Bodine</hi> Droling <hi>facetiouſly</hi> upon the <hi>proceeding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Metarini Hiſt. Belg. Lib. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed riſu dignares eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod non modo Genuenſibus verum etiam Philippo, &amp;c.</hi> It was thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant and ridicule that not only the <hi>Genoeſes</hi> but <hi>Phillip</hi> alſo ſhould be interdicted, he, becauſe he took money to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> they, becauſe they lent it. However they were both (this being done only by <hi>compact,</hi> and to give the better grace to this neat <hi>Emuncture</hi> or <hi>wipe</hi>) in a little time ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in this caſe the <hi>Intereſt</hi> Money was and is <hi>punctually ſatisfyed, and I wiſh I could affirm as much in ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I do not find that this <hi>Debt</hi> of the <hi>Genoeſes</hi> was <hi>ſecured</hi> unto them by any <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Cortes</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and ſo the <hi>Common Faith</hi> of that <hi>Nation</hi> inviolate. But in our <hi>caſe,</hi> our <hi>Debt</hi> is ſecured to the <hi>Bankers</hi> and their <hi>Aſſignees</hi> by <hi>National Obligation,</hi> As I have (I think) above moſt evidently proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly, Campanella</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> a man of infinite <hi>ſubtility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Campanella Span. Mon. chap. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and one that ſeems to be even <hi>anxious,</hi> and eaten up with <hi>zeal</hi> for the <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the which he <hi>cultivates</hi> with a ſingular <hi>diligence</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe of that Monarchy.</hi> This very <hi>man,</hi> I ſay, doth with all his <hi>vigor,</hi> not only <hi>adviſe,</hi> but <hi>importune</hi> King <hi>Phillip</hi> with all <hi>ſpeed</hi> to pay this <hi>Debt</hi> to the <hi>Genoeſes. Leaſt</hi> ſaith he (among other reaſons there given) <hi>if there ſhould happen any Riſing in</hi> Italy <hi>to the prejudice of that King the</hi> Genoan <hi>Banners might march alſo along with them for company.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>I ſhall (I hope) <hi>auſpiciouſly</hi> take the riſe of my <hi>Concluſion</hi> from two me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable <hi>Records.</hi> The one relating to <hi>Widdowes</hi> and <hi>Orphans,</hi> the other to thoſe <hi>Worthies</hi> who with their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> had many years agoe <hi>propugn'd</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which concerns the <hi>former</hi> I ſhall for the excellency thereof (ſo far as it concerns my purpoſe) tranſcribe <hi>verbatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Die veneris proxime ante Feſtum beati</hi> Edwardi, <hi>Anno Regni</hi> Regis
<pb facs="tcp:51796:20"/>Henrici tertii 34. <hi>venit Dominus</hi> Rex <hi>cum ſuo</hi> Concilio <hi>ad</hi> ſcaccarium <hi>&amp; ibidem</hi> proprio ore <hi>praecepit omnibus</hi> vicecomitibus Angliae,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>InterCommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia termino</hi> Mich. <hi>35.</hi> Hen. <hi>3.</hi> in Officio Remen. Theſ. in Scac. Rot. <hi>2.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. praeceptum Doms. Regis</note> 
                  <hi>tunc ibidem exiſtentibus. Imprimis quod modis omnibus obſervarent &amp; manutenerent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertates ſanctae Eccleſiae, &amp; ſimiliter manutenerent Pupillos Orphanos, &amp; viduas &amp; celerem eis juſticiam exhbierent, &amp;c.</hi> Here we have, it Regiſtred in the <hi>Records</hi> of <hi>Fame,</hi> that the glorious <hi>King Henry</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> came in his <hi>own perſon</hi> into his Court of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> environ'd with his Illuſtrious <hi>Councellors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 29.14.</note> and there with <hi>his own mouth</hi> gave it in charge to all the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> That in the firſt place (next after holy <hi>Church</hi>) they ſhould <hi>Defend</hi> the <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>Widdows,</hi> and <hi>do unto them ſpeedy Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other <hi>Record</hi> is that of 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. where that Renowned <hi>King</hi> gives expreſs <hi>Order</hi> that a <hi>Roll</hi> ſhould be forthwith made of ſuch <hi>perſons</hi> which had ſpent their <hi>Youths</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> in the ſervice of his <hi>Royal Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>11.</hi> Hea. <hi>6.</hi> Memh <hi>6.</hi> Cok <hi>54th.</hi> Inſt <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6.</hi> Rot. Parl. <hi>8.</hi> Hen. <hi>6.</hi> Memb. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Himſelf,</hi> to the intent that ſuch of them (I ſhall give you the very words of the <hi>Record</hi>) which are without any <hi>Livelyhood,</hi> or<note n="*" place="margin">Reward.</note> 
                  <hi>Guerdon,</hi> and ſo in great <hi>miſchief</hi> and <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and ſome but eaſily <hi>Guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned,</hi> and nought like to their <hi>Deſert</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> may, when <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Benefices</hi> fall, have them confer'd upon them, &amp;c. I hope no body will think me ſo <hi>preſumptuous</hi> or <hi>vain,</hi> as to preſcribe this for an <hi>Example;</hi> I know when we have ſerved <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> with our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> we are notwithſtanding <hi>unprofitable Servants,</hi> and have ſtill done but our <hi>indiſpenſable duties,</hi> only this I ſhall ſay (and I ſpeak it with an humble <hi>modeſty</hi>) That I hope we that were <hi>Sufferers</hi> for our <hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſhall be thought now, as worthy of enjoying thoſe poor <hi>Remnants</hi> and <hi>Scraps</hi> of our <hi>Fortanes,</hi> as theſe <hi>perſons</hi> before us were of receiving their <hi>Guerdons</hi> and <hi>Rewards.</hi> I do never without a ſecret <hi>exaltation</hi> of <hi>Mind</hi> conſider this following <hi>Memoire</hi> that I find of <hi>Aug ſius Caeſar:</hi> upon the Defeat (ſaith my Author) of <hi>Mark Antony</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> famous Battail of <hi>Actium, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> commenc'd <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">vita Octavis Auguſti, bound up in <hi>Plutarch's Lives.</hi>
                  </note> ſome few yeaas after, a certain old <hi>Souldier</hi> (that in this Battail had done <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſar</hi> good ſervice) hapned to be impleaded for his <hi>Life</hi> before his <hi>Imperiat Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Senate;</hi> The <hi>Soldier</hi> implores <hi>Caeſar</hi> (then preſent) to help him in this <hi>Diſireſs, Caeſar</hi> recommended him to an able <hi>Adoccate,</hi> the routh <hi>Soldier</hi> not contented with this, forthwith <hi>rips</hi> open his <hi>boſome,</hi> and expoſing to the <hi>view</hi> of the whole <hi>Court</hi> the marks of the <hi>Wounds</hi> which he had received at the ſaid Battaile of <hi>Actium; Theſe wounds</hi> (quoth he) <hi>O</hi> Caeſar <hi>have I received on my mangled body in thy defence, and ſubſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uted no Deputy in my place! Auguſtus</hi> hereupon (overwhelm'd with the <hi>Paſſionateneſs</hi> of this <hi>Action</hi>) preſently <hi>ſtood</hi> up and pleaded the <hi>Soldiers Cauſe</hi> himſelf, and carried it. An <hi>Action</hi> certainly well beſeeming an <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>World!</hi> And are there not many miſerable <hi>perſons</hi> concern'd now with
<pb facs="tcp:51796:20"/>the <hi>Bankers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Fathers, Husbands, Children,</hi> and other <hi>Relations</hi> have aſſerted the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> with their deareſt <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes?</hi> nay, are not ſeveral of <hi>that kind</hi> yet ſurviving, which do yet bear in their miſerable bodies the <hi>Scars</hi> and glorious <hi>Remarks</hi> of their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Battails of <hi>Edge-hil, Newberry, Nasby, Worceſter,</hi> and indeed where not? And ſhall we imagine that our <hi>Caeſar</hi> (a <hi>Prince</hi> of ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi>) will ſuffer theſe <hi>perſons</hi> and their <hi>Families</hi> to <hi>ſtarve</hi> for <hi>want</hi> of that which is their <hi>own?</hi> And that he will not <hi>proceed</hi> (as he hath begun) to be an <hi>Advocate</hi> and <hi>Interceſſor</hi> for them in ſo juſt a <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare be confident his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is inexpreſſibly ſenſible of this <hi>Calamity,</hi> which is fallen upon <hi>us,</hi> and his Royal <hi>Bowels</hi> yerne with <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. Neither is the <hi>Delay</hi> of <hi>Payment</hi> hitherto any <hi>Defect</hi> in His <hi>Majeſty's</hi> innate <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but an <hi>Excreſſence</hi> and unhappy <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetation</hi> of the firſt pernicious <hi>Councel</hi> of Shutting the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> to think otherwiſe were to <hi>blaſpheme</hi> the greateſt ſweetneſs of <hi>Nature</hi> in the world, And to <hi>prophane</hi> that Illuſtrious <hi>Prince,</hi> of whom no man ever yet form'd a thought, but his mind was preſently fild with the <hi>Idea</hi> of all that is <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part I am no <hi>Projector,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> have alwayes in my own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture abhominated all <hi>Vermine</hi> of that kinde; But yet me thinks it is not impoſſible to deſigne a <hi>Courſe</hi> how to pay off this Debt of the <hi>Bankers,</hi> and that by waies not only <hi>practicable</hi> and <hi>Legal,</hi> but <hi>Grateful</hi> alſo to the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> am not ignorant that <hi>I</hi> have here all along in this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> dealt in an <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>ſublimity</hi> and <hi>importance,</hi> of which a man can hardly write perhaps without being in ſome meaſure <hi>Sacrilegious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.3 <hi>and</hi> 4.</note> But yet we find that our Saviour Chriſt excuſed the ſervants of King <hi>David,</hi> when they were ready to periſh for want of food, though they broke into the Houſe of <hi>God,</hi> and made bold with the holy <hi>Bread.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stamfords Pleas of the Crown.</note> And the Law of this Land ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quits the perſon that ſteals <hi>viands</hi> to pacify the preſent <hi>Languiſhments</hi> of nature. Where the purturbations of the <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> are ſo great, as in preſumption of Law, man's <hi>Nature</hi> cannot overcome, ſuch <hi>neceſſity</hi> carryeth a <hi>Priviledge</hi> in it ſelf;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ld.</hi> Bacon's Maxims of Law, pa. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> (ſaith no mean Author) And <hi>I</hi> hope that <hi>man</hi> ſhall not be thought <hi>pragmatical</hi> or <hi>buſy</hi> that deals in a <hi>matter</hi> in which the Fates of his <hi>Ruine</hi> or <hi>Happineſs</hi> are <hi>imbarck't.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There be many things which poſſibly <hi>I</hi> have <hi>forgot,</hi> and ſome things which <hi>I</hi> have perhaps induſtriouſly <hi>omitted.</hi> If any matter have fallen from me <hi>inconſiderately,</hi> (as in ſo long a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> may eaſily happen) <hi>I</hi> do with unſpeakable <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>Proſtration</hi> beg <hi>Pardon,</hi> requeſting this one <hi>Favour,</hi> that no perſons would cenſure me, or thoſe worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in my condition, until they have firſt repreſented our <hi>Caſes</hi> to them ſelves, as their own.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:51796:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proteſting</hi> in the laſt place that I have written nothing but with a <hi>mind</hi> at all times ready to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> it dwells in to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of my Gracious <hi>Soveraign</hi> and his <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> And upon that glorious account, prepared alwayes to ſuffer more, then <hi>He</hi> or <hi>They</hi> deſerve; that adviſed His Majeſty to the ſtopping the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Illud omnium maximè tenendum erit a Princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ut fortunis alienis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per atum fuiſſe cognoſcatur: Nam citius parentum cadem oblivioni dant Homines; quam Fortunarum ſuarum direptione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Nic. Machiavelli princeps, Cap. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>His Majeſties <hi>Declaration</hi> To all His Loving Subjects, to preſerve Inviolable the <hi>Securities</hi> by Him given for <hi>Moneys,</hi> and the due Courſe of Payments thereupon in the Receipt of the EXCHEQUER.</head>
            <p>WHereas <hi>We</hi> are given to underſtand, That divers of Our good and <hi>Loyal Subjects, Goldſmiths</hi> and others, who have advanced to Us great Summs of Money for the Publick <hi>Service,</hi> which are ſufficiently ſecured unto them upon ſeveral Branches of Our <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,</hi> and other <hi>moneys</hi> ariſing by ſeveral late Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have upon occaſion taken from the late At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the <hi>Dutch Fleet,</hi> and the falſe <hi>Reports</hi> ſpread there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, been preſt in an unuſual manner, with many ſudden <hi>Demands</hi> by their <hi>Creditors,</hi> for preſent <hi>Payment,</hi> through <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſions;</hi> which may weaken the <hi>Credit</hi> of Our ſaid <hi>Subjects,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> who have been ſo <hi>uſeful</hi> to Us bring an <hi>undervalue</hi> on Our ſaid <hi>Securities,</hi> and in conſequence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the <hi>Publick Safety</hi> in this preſent Conjunctur: We have therefore thought fit (as well for ſatisfying the minds of our good Subjects, whoſe fears ſo tranſported them to call for their <hi>moneys</hi> in ſuch a manner; as for the allaying ſuch Jealouſies and miſapprehenſions as may be taken up by thoſe concerned in the ſaid <hi>Securities</hi>) to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, as we do hereby declare, that as the <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in our <hi>Exchequer</hi> hath hitherto been punctual, and according to the due <hi>Order,</hi> even in this time of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and interruption of Payments amongſt our <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;</hi> ſo <hi>Our</hi> ſtedfaſt reſolution for preſerving inviolable
<pb facs="tcp:51796:22"/>to all ſuch Our good Subjects, who have <hi>Lent</hi> or <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> any moneys for <hi>Our</hi> ſervice as aforeſaid, All and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very the <hi>Securities</hi> and <hi>Aſſignements</hi> any wayes made by <hi>Us</hi> for and towards the <hi>Repayment</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of the ſaid ſeveral ſumms of money:<note place="margin">☞</note> And that <hi>We</hi> will not upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſion whatſoever <hi>permit</hi> or <hi>ſuffer</hi> any <hi>Alteration, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation,</hi> or <hi>Interruption</hi> to be made of our ſaid <hi>Subjects Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities;</hi> but that they ſhall from <hi>time</hi> to <hi>time</hi> receive the <hi>Moneys</hi> ſo <hi>ſecured</hi> unto them, in the ſame <hi>Courſe</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> as they were <hi>charged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> and <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> Which <hi>reſolution</hi> we ſhall likewiſe hold <hi>firm</hi> and ſacred, in all <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> Aſſignements and <hi>Securities</hi> to be by Us Granted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other <hi>Advance</hi> of <hi>Money</hi> by any of our Subjects upon any Future <hi>Occaſion</hi> for Our <hi>Service.</hi> And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt upon the publiſhing this our <hi>Royal Word</hi> and <hi>Declaration</hi> of our ſincere <hi>Intention,</hi> but that all reaſonable perſons will reſt ſatisfied that their fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s were cauſeleſs, &amp; their reſpective Intereſts in no danger at all, and that no evil can happen to them on this Occaſion; ſince the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curites</hi> by Us to them given being inviolable, we doubt not but that our ſaid <hi>Subjects</hi> will ſatisfie every perſon both their <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as they have formerly done with untainted <hi>Reputation.</hi> And of this our <hi>Declaration</hi> we ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge and Command our High <hi>Chancellor</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the Lords Commiſſioners of our Treaſury, the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor and Under-Treaſurer of our <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and all other our Officers and Miniſters whatſoever whom it doth or may concern, to take notice and duly to obſerve the ſame, as they will be anſwerable to Us at their utmoſt perils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given at Our Court at whitehall, this</hi> 18th. <hi>day of</hi> June 1667. <hi>And in the Nineteenth year of Our Reign.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:22"/>
            <head>THE Poſtſcript TO THE Letter.</head>
            <p>THus (Sir) I have (as you ſee according to the <hi>Model</hi> of my weak <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi>) diſcovered the <hi>Enormity</hi> and pernicious <hi>Influences</hi> of this <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake God to witneſs I have done this, without the leaſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> or <hi>Deſigne</hi> againſt any man's perſon, of what <hi>Degree</hi> or <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſoever; Indeed if any man ſhall come from behind the <hi>Curtain</hi> &amp; with a <hi>bare &amp;</hi> open <hi>face</hi> ſhall ſay <hi>I am the Man that gave this Advice.</hi> That per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I muſt confeſs (and only that perſon) hath not eſcapt my <hi>Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and from <hi>him</hi> only, and no <hi>body</hi> elſe I hope I can with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> expect <hi>Reproof.</hi> And then let all <hi>Mankind</hi> judge, whether of the two is more to be blamed, he that hath lead his <hi>Prince</hi> out of the <hi>old via Regia</hi> or King's high way, into by and <hi>untrodden Paths,</hi> unknown <hi>to the Law,</hi> and to walk upon <hi>Precipices,</hi> or he that hath given an honeſt <hi>Alarm</hi> or <hi>Outcry</hi> of this evil <hi>Dealing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh</hi> (under whoſe old <hi>Engliſh Councels</hi> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> flouriſht, and became <hi>formidable</hi> to all the world,<note place="margin">Cottoni poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma <hi>p. 313.</hi>
               </note> and one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that better underſtood the <hi>Genius</hi> and <hi>temper</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi> then this <hi>Adviſor</hi>) was uſed to tell his Queen. <hi>Madam</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>Win Hearts and you'l be ſure of Hands and Purſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">vita Dionis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And <hi>Dion</hi> (in <hi>Plutarch</hi>) doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the Son of King <hi>Dionyſius. That the Love of the ſubject (obtaind by vertue and Juſtice) is the ſtrongeſt guard and ſecurity of a Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> and my own <hi>Conſcience</hi> will be my <hi>Compurgators</hi> and Witneſſes, that whatever I have ſaid in this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> I have done it with a moſt ardent and paſſionate <hi>Deſire</hi> of the <hi>Prosperity</hi> of my dread <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and an unfeined <hi>Love</hi> to my dear <hi>Countreymen,</hi> and to raiſe and <hi>enkindle</hi> (as well as I could) an univerſal <hi>Dispoſition</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome</hi> towards the <hi>Payment</hi> of this <hi>Debt;</hi> That thereupon ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:51796:23"/>a <hi>part</hi> of the Engliſh <hi>Nation</hi> (as are concern'd with the <hi>Bankers</hi>) may not be <hi>overwhelm'd</hi> with an inevitable <hi>Ruine,</hi> and that ſo great a <hi>Member</hi> thereof may not be raviſht and <hi>torn limbmeal</hi> from the <hi>Body</hi> of this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall probably be thought by ſome perſons to have proſecuted this <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> with a warmer <hi>Zeal</hi> then became mee, and to have <hi>ſallied</hi> out ſometimes perhaps into <hi>Extravagancies</hi> and <hi>Inconſideration:</hi> I can only <hi>Reply,</hi> that the <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> by me vouched, are <hi>Authentique,</hi> and of approved <hi>Credit,</hi> and by me <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>carefully quoted,</hi> That after I have ſacrificed my <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> to mine <hi>Allegiance</hi> in the Late <hi>Rebellion;</hi> no man I hope will ſuppoſe that I ſhould now become <hi>Apoſtate</hi> or <hi>Renegado</hi> to ſo <hi>glorious a Cauſe, That Neceſſity, and the want of a mans own, are ſpurs ſharp and invincible;</hi> And <hi>Laſtly</hi> that I have been <hi>actuated</hi> all along in this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> with no other <hi>Impulſes</hi> of <hi>mind,</hi> then thoſe which looſen'd the <hi>Tongue</hi> of the <hi>Dumb</hi> Son of King <hi>Craeſus,</hi> when he ſaw a <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier</hi> ready to offer <hi>violence</hi> to his <hi>Father</hi> crying out, <hi>It is the King!</hi> At whoſe <hi>Royal Feet</hi> I am alwayes ready upon <hi>Occaſion</hi> to lay down my <hi>Life,</hi> together with that poor <hi>Mite</hi> or <hi>Fragment</hi> of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> which the <hi>Rebbeis</hi> and this <hi>Adviſor</hi> have left me: Praying (in the <hi>Scripture</hi> Language) <hi>That God would ſtrike through the Loins of all them that hate His Majeſty, but that upon his own Head his Crown may for ever flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Sir your moſt Affectionate Servant, S. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Some faults thou art deſired to amend, which by reaſon of the abſence of the Author, and haſte, have eſcaped the Preſs. As in the third page of the Letter in the firſt ſheet, Line 18. for <hi>irradicated</hi> read <hi>irradiated,</hi> &amp;c. The Poyntings alſo in many places are to be amended.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51796:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
